<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of ministers maintenance by tithes, (as in England,) plainly discussed in conscience and prudence. Humbly propounded to the consideration of those gentlemen of the committee, who are in consultation about it. / By John Gauden, D.D.</title>
            <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E220_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3663</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872455</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872455</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124892</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85845)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124892)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 38:E220[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of ministers maintenance by tithes, (as in England,) plainly discussed in conscience and prudence. Humbly propounded to the consideration of those gentlemen of the committee, who are in consultation about it. / By John Gauden, D.D.</title>
                  <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Maxey, for Andrew Crook, and are to be sold at the signe of the Green Dragon in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Finance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124892:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:124892:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The CASE OF MINISTERS MAINTENANCE BY TITHES, (As in ENGLAND,) Plainly diſcuſſed in CONSCIENCE and PRUDENCE.</p>
            <p>Humbly propounded to the conſideration of thoſe Gentlemen of the Committee, who are in conſultation about it.</p>
            <p>BY JOHN GAUDEN, <hi>D. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>TIT. 11.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>That thou mayeſt be able by ſound Doctrine, both to exhort, and convince the gainſayers.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Maxey,</hi> for <hi>Andrew Crook,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:124892:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124892:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Caſe of MINISTERS MAINTENANCE By TITHES,</hi> Humbly preſented to the Gentlemen of the Committee.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Preſume, it will offend none of you, if you are Godly, <hi>with meekneſs of wiſdome</hi> to hear what may bee the judgment of other men, who are ſtanders by; yet as much concerned in thoſe matters you now handle, of publick intereſt, as your ſelfs; whoſe preſent place and power, as they add not to your, ſo they detract not from other mens <hi>rationall or Religious abilities.</hi> Yea ſuch I hear is the modeſty and equanimity of ſome of you, as not to lay any ſupercilious reſtraints, or tyrannous obſtructions in the way of any ſober man, but rather to invite and expect ſeaſonable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes and diſcreet diſcoveries of other mens ſenſe; however differing from yours; as in other things, ſo in this of <hi>Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> as it hath been many hundred of years by Cuſtome or Law ſetled here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which (as in all affairs of great concernement) <hi>violent changes,</hi> and precipitant reſolutions (gratifying the preſent heats and paſſions of any men) may ſoon create many and irremediable miſcheifes to the people of this Nation; But well adviſed and impartial counſels may (through Gods bleſſing) by their Juſtice, Piety and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, not only prevent thoſe farther troubles and confuſions, which are by many feared, by ſome threatned, and by others hoped; But alſo add much honor, peace and proſperity to theſe Britiſh Churches and Nations; both as to civil and Religious affairs; In
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124892:3"/> which your and your poſterities welfare is bound up, as well, as that of your brethren.</p>
            <p>Therefore in a matter of ſo much conſequence, as this ſeems to be, (how-ever I am ſorry there ſhould bee any occaſion for me, or any man to repreſent anew, what Truths have been ſo learnedly and largely handled by able men, and publiſhed to the Engliſh world;) yet I hope, I may without offence take leave (which I humbly crave) with all <hi>Chriſtian meeknes,</hi> to offer to your wiſdome theſe following conſiderations. Which are drawn either from <hi>clear demonſtrations</hi> of the mind of God ſet forth in his Word; or from <hi>the evidence of right reaſon</hi> and common equity.</p>
            <p>Both which I muſt in charity ſuppoſe to bee the rules and bounds of your purpoſes and motions; as they ought to be of all wiſe mens deliberations,<note place="margin">Iſai. 32.16 17 Gal. 6.16.</note> reſolutions, and actions; Being the only fountains whence truth, righteouſnes and peace do flow: And the beſt defenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives againſt thoſe temptations, which uſually attend ignorance, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, partiality, and thoſe tranſports of fears, envy, revenge, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs and ambition, incident to the minds and manners of frail and ſinful mortals, whoſe momentany follys and ſudden miſcarriages oft produce laſting calamities, which are farre more eaſily prevented then removed: when once, as fire or water, they have prevailed to outrages and exceſſes, after times may ſadly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they cannot remedy in this kind; There being few examples to be found or hoped for, of renewed bounty; reſtoring to the Church of Chriſt, any thing that our <hi>ſacrilegious raſhnes,</hi> or cruelty hath devouted</p>
            <p>And leaſt you or any man ſhould be prejudiced, againſt what ever may here be offred by <hi>mee</hi> in this point of <hi>Miniſters maintenance;</hi> as if I aimed hereby to preſerve any private benefit to my ſelf by my Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical living; I do here freely offer to relinquiſh it, (if I be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to required) in order to confirm the integrity of my judgment in this point: That you and all men may ſee, no private advantages ſway me, who, in order to preſerve the liberty and livelyhoods of others, my <hi>Fathers and Brethren of the Miniſtery;</hi> had rather preach the <hi>Gospel gratis,</hi> (ſo long as God enables mee), then to enjoy the greateſt emolument you or any man can give mee. Which I ſhould eſteem as <hi>loſſe and dung,</hi> while I ſee the reformed Religion ſtarved; the Name of Chriſt blaſphemed; his faithful miniſters diſcouraged, and by moſt indigne injuries expoſed, either to ſordid neceſſities or uncomly dependances; ſuch as would move griefe and ſhame to any godly man; How much then would he abhorre to be agent of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in ſuch unjuſt oppreſſions and diminutions? wherein none can rejoyce or willingly act, but ſuch as are enemys to the <hi>reformed Religion,</hi> and to the happines of this nation; Againſt both which, there are not wanting ſuch <hi>deep Policies</hi> and <hi>desperate deſignes,</hi> domeſtick
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124892:3"/> and forrain, as hope in a ſhort time to deſtroy and devour them both. Which miſeries, if you in your time and place, do not ſtudy to prevent, but either by weaknes or wilfulnes promote, you ſhall never want the guilt of great <hi>ſin</hi> before God, and of laſting <hi>infamy</hi> before men; The aggravations of both which are to be taken from thoſe proportions of publick power and influence, which any men, at any time pretend to enjoy and exerciſe in Church or State; which make them in an higher nature and degree reſponſible to God and man for the evil they do, or the good they hinder; as we ſee in <hi>Eli,</hi> in his ſons, in <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and others. This is certain, They who undertake to <hi>rule</hi> others, charge themſelves in many reſpects with <hi>the ſouls of men,</hi> and are accountable before God and man for other mens both ſins and miſeries.</p>
            <p>BUt here, before I preſent to your conſiderations the point of <hi>Miniſters maintenance,</hi> I hope it will not be expected by you, (or imputed to me, as any defect, ſince it is not now my deſigne, to aſſert <hi>the Inſtitution, Calling, Office, Divine Authority,</hi> excellency and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>Evangelical Miniſtry.</hi> Which ſome men, to make ſhort work, and to ſweep away all ſtakes at one throw, do, either abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deny to be any where in the Church of Chriſt; or not ſuch as it ought to be in this <hi>Church of England;</hi> ſo that either no Tithes, or other ſetled Maintenance is due to any men, as Miniſters; or at leaſt, not to theſe, that <hi>here claime</hi> them as <hi>Such.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is too large a controverſie for me in this place to handle; which other where hath been largely done, through Gods aſſiſtance, and as I hope, to his glory, among the children of true wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Thus much only at preſent I make bold to ſuggeſt to you; Do but as wiſe and unpartial men, 1. ſeparate from the <hi>Country people,</hi> their ruſtick Confidences, their Credulity, &amp; Eaſines, their Peeviſhnes, Envie, and Antipathy to men of better breeding and manners; beſides their Covetouſnes, and what ſavours of the <hi>Clod,</hi> or thick clay, with which they ſeek <hi>to load themſelves:</hi> Alſo 2. Take away from men of <hi>finer metal,</hi> their deſire of novelty, their factiouſneſs, their liſting to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, their vain glory, their licentious inclinations, their warpings to ſelf intereſts, which love not to be reproved or reſtrained by any ſeverer doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or manners. 3. Laſtly, ſift and ſearch more narrowly the <hi>finer deſignes</hi> and <hi>deeper projects</hi> of <hi>Pragmatiſts</hi> and <hi>Politians;</hi> the imperiouſnes of whoſe luſts are inconſiſtent with thoſe ſtrict rules of righteouſneſs, truth and holineſs, by which they are impatient to be diſcovered or checked. Look, I ſay, but apart, on this droſſe, which is naturaly in all ſorts of men; And then as Chriſtians you will ſoon underſtand, what are the main grounds of ſo many mens cavilling and contending againſt the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> both as to their Office and Maintenance.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:124892:4"/>
            <p>It is humbly confeſſed, as we are men, we are ſubject to as many infirmities, as any earthen veſſels; and, as we are <hi>Miniſters,</hi> we are liable to more temptations and oppoſitions both from men and divels; yet as to the duty, dignity, and uſefulneſs of the calling, it cannot be denyed, that many holy, humble, wiſe, and <hi>contented Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> have for many ages highly valued, and ſincerely loved it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they happily profited by it. For this they have often and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feinedly <hi>bleſſed God.</hi> For this <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> they now earneſtly pray, that it may be continued to them and theirs: by this they acknowledg to have received their <hi>greateſt good,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus. And to it they <hi>grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully confeſs</hi> they ow even their own ſouls; as to the means, (under God) of their inſtruction, ſanctification and ſalvation.</p>
            <p>We may not now reproach any mens ingratitude, being ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to our own failings and deformities: It muſt be confeſſed, that the people of this nation ow their troubles to the ſins, Ignorance, Pride and Policy of Miniſters, as well as People: we know it is not a time roughly to teſt but fairely to plead our cauſe; whoſe deſire is not to uphold our Calling, that we may enjoy <hi>Maintenance;</hi> But to continue <hi>juſt Maintenance,</hi> that we may preſerve the honor and bleſſing of the Calling to Poſterity.</p>
            <p>For which Miniſters do not urge what is moſt evident by long <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> and <hi>many Lawes</hi> in this Nation: that they have had and ſtill have poſſeſſion of that Maintenance, which the <hi>Law</hi> hath aſſigned to them; That their title is as good as any mans by Law to his eſtate. That, it were an intollerable vexation to put men to prove by what right they hold thoſe Eſtates, which their Predeceſſors and themſelves have without moleſtation enjoyed for a <hi>thouſand years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It reſts in thoſe that would diſpoſſeſſe them to diſprove their right and claime; ſince they are ſuch <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and ſo inveſted in their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, as the Law required.</p>
            <p>Nor do they plead for their Office and Maintenance that <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal approbation,</hi> which all forrain <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> have ever given to them; neither of which their adverſaries have either invalidated or queſtioned.</p>
            <p>Conſciencious Miniſters are ſo ingenuous, as not to deſire to enjoy their <hi>Maintenance,</hi> by the favour of the Law, if they cannot, before any <hi>impartial Tribunal,</hi> firſt, maintain their Callin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Miniſtry as Chriſts, both by Scripture grounds, and Eccleſiaſtical examples, conform thereto in all ages, ſince <hi>Chriſts Aſcenſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if theſe were leſſe pregnant for their vindication; yet the excellent <hi>Miniſterial gifts,</hi> with which many of them have been endued; The many <hi>gracious works,</hi> which the Lord hath wrought by them; their <hi>Spiritual bleſſings,</hi> which they have imparted; their ſound preaching, their judicions praying, their decent &amp; comfortable
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124892:4"/> 
               <hi>celebrating</hi> of <hi>Holy Myſteries;</hi> their <hi>wholſom Doctrine;</hi> their <hi>ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate</hi> writings; their <hi>Holy living;</hi> theſe will teſtifie for them and their Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>
               </label> The conſciences and ſouls alſo of many thouſand Chriſtians <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>living</hi> would give witneſſe to them, that they are the true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Jeſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.2.</note> The holy and happy fruits of their labours have every where pregnantly <hi>ſealed</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> the power and authority of their Miniſtry, however as men they had their fayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>It argues groſſe blindneſs in mens eies, to deny the light of the Sun, when it is preſent; which is ſufficient to prove it ſelf, to men that have ſight, and are willing to ſee; It is loſt labour to aſſert either <hi>Miniſtry</hi> or <hi>Maintenance</hi> before thoſe, who deny them upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, either to ſave mony by having no Miniſters at all; or to get all the Maintenance to themſelves, by being the only Miniſters, though of no <hi>legitimate</hi> ſucceſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>
               </label> Men, full as learned, godly, and wiſe, as any that now pretend moſt to Piety and Prudence, have both privately and publickely, owned, honoured, loved, and preſerved both the <hi>Miniſtry of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and its Maintenance.</hi> In which number you may be, if you have that <hi>low and modeſt</hi> eſteeme of your ſelfs, which beſt becomes you; who have little reaſon, (if you look to the rock whence you are hewen, and to the hole of the pit whence ye are digged, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.1. being but extraordinary, and temporary Pilots, applyed to the <hi>helm</hi> of this State,) to preferre <hi>your counſels</hi> or concluſions before thoſe of your wiſe and godly fore fathers; nor to advance your power, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their undoubted authoritie, by removing thoſe ancient land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks which they have ſet for many generations.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>
               </label> Leaving therefore the Office and Calling of Miniſters, as ſelf <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating,</hi> to all that are truly gracious Chriſtians; I take libertie to proceed <hi>more largely,</hi> upon <hi>their Maintenance;</hi> as it is ſetled in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> chiefly by <hi>Tithes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching which there can be but <hi>two grand</hi> conſiderations offered to wiſe men, or entertained by them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, that of <hi>duty and neceſſity,</hi> ariſing from <hi>Divine precept,</hi> ſtrictly binding; in caſes, where the <hi>will of God</hi> is preciſely and clearly ſet forth in his Holy Word, either <hi>bidding,</hi> or <hi>forbidding</hi> any thing; which caſes admit no diſpute, but exact ready obedience from all men under pain of ſin and wrath.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is, that of <hi>choice and conveniency;</hi> wherein <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prudence</hi> may uſe that rational and Religious freedome, which ſhall in private or publicke caſes ſeem beſt to them; not being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely determined or limited by the Divine wiſdome; but left to the <hi>diſcretion</hi> of wiſe and Godly men, in their perſons or places; in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124892:5"/> or Policies; ſo as ſtill to regard the <hi>main ends,</hi> which the Lord hath in general propounded. In ſuch things Chriſtians may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly chuſe and act things leſſe <hi>prudent and convenient;</hi> yet without the blame of <hi>ſin before</hi> God; although not without the reproach of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence and weaknes before men.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt ground upon which conſcience muſt be ſetled; (wherein great care muſt be bad neither to <hi>multiply ſin</hi> beyond the Law of God,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cl. 7.16.</note> by an <hi>unrighteous ſcrupaloſity;</hi> nor to diminiſh them by any <hi>looſe indifferency.</hi>) Three <hi>Quaeres</hi> are by ſober men to bee examined.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quere </seg>1</label> 1. Firſt whether the competent and comely Maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, at other <hi>mens coſts</hi> and charges (in caſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters require it) bee expreſly commanded by the Lord? or may by clear and neceſſarie conſequence bee gathered <hi>out of his holy word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. To this, the <hi>Anſwer</hi> muſt be <hi>Affirmative.</hi> There being many clear places declaring the <hi>right and power of Miniſters</hi> to claime:<note place="margin">1 Cor 9.6. Gal. 6.6.</note> and commanding people to retribute ſuch Maintenance to them, out of their Eſtates, as is due in common equity and gratitude: ſuch as conſtant experience, light of nature, and every mans own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience dictates, requires, juſtifies; So that the <hi>Oxes-feeding</hi> of the corn he treads;<note place="margin">Luk. 10.7.</note> The <hi>Labourers hire</hi> for his work; The <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> benefit of the ground he tils; The <hi>Shepherds</hi> ſuſtenance by the <hi>ſtock</hi> he feeds; theſe are not more pregnant and neceſſary claimes of juſtice, than is that of the <hi>Miniſters of the</hi> Goſpel; as the Apoſtle proves in particular inſtances: 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. from v. 7. to v. 14. and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour layes down in one general maxime, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To thoſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſubjoines, as a further <hi>expreſſe decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the will of God in this caſe of Miniſters maintenance;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.13.14.</note> both as to the conſtant juſtice of it; and that exemplarines as to the <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> and proportion, which his wiſdome and bounty had formely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for his <hi>Miniſters at the Altar;</hi> For whom, as the Lord made a particular and plentiful proviſion, even ſo hee hath now ordained, that the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel. Not upon <hi>alms</hi> and meer benevolence, after the way of begging uncertaintie, or ſhameful <hi>ſharking</hi> and neceſſity; ſparingly and grudgingly; but, as becomes the Name of God, the honor of Chriſt, the dignity of their embaſſie, the uſefulneſs of their labours in the word and doctrine,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.2. Tit. 1.8. 1 Tim 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>competently, comfortably,</hi> hoſpitably, and honorably. Treating them as Parents, with <hi>double honor;</hi> that is, <hi>Reverence,</hi> and <hi>ingenuous Maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>
               </label> 3. Nor can this ſeem much in the eies of <hi>good Chriſtians,</hi> who wiſely weigh and conſider the great diſproportion, which is between thoſe <hi>Spiritual good</hi> things,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.11.</note> which they receive from God by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124892:5"/> tending to the eternal good of their ſouls; and theſe <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral good</hi> things, which they retribute in gratitude and juſtice, which are but <hi>carnal,</hi> onely for the outward man, fading, uncertain; and but for a moment in compariſon.</p>
            <p>So that whoſoever hath once taſted effectually the comfort and benefit to be had in <hi>ſpiritual things,</hi> (whereof Miniſters are Gods ordinary <hi>diſpenſers</hi>) will never grudge to impart to him <hi>that teacheth</hi> him, of <hi>all his good things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> which conſcience both of common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and Gods expreſs command binds him to; ſo inexcuſable are thoſe before God and man, who partaking, by their Miniſters pains, of the <hi>excellency of the knowledg of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> think much to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to them in <hi>Chriſts Name,</hi> and for Gods ſake, of thoſe things which are but loſſe and dung in compariſon.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>4</label> Yea further, becauſe <hi>Military man,</hi> or <hi>Souldiers,</hi> are prone to meaſure all right by <hi>their power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.7.</note> and to own no other <hi>rule of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> but their will and ſword; The bleſſed Apoſtle, to ſtop their <hi>mouths</hi> from opening againſt the <hi>maintenance of Miniſters,</hi> and to leave them ſelf-condemned, if they grudg at or detain the <hi>ſalary</hi> or <hi>pay,</hi> which theſe have for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>warring in a better warfare;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.3.</note> not at their own, but other mens charges, gives that particular Inſtance, among others; <hi>Who goeth to war at his own coſt?</hi> So that no Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier may without ſhame and <hi>ſelf-conviction</hi> ſpeak againſt Miniſters maintenance, who himſelf not only receives pay, but exacts it; nor as a <hi>benevolence,</hi> and arbitrary, but and juſtice and neceſſary: When the Souldiers fight <hi>gratis,</hi> upon <hi>their own charges,</hi> and take no pay; then let them declaim againſt the ſetled <hi>maintenance of Miniſters:</hi> Till then; they ought in all equity and honour to plead for them, and preſerve their Rights to them.</p>
            <p>Which rights are derived to them from God and the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who hath the <hi>Supream dominion</hi> over all mens perſons and eſtates, who hath the aſſigned this power and right to them, ſo far as they are his ſervants, Meſſengers, and Embaſſadors in Chriſts ſtead, ordaining that <hi>they who preach the Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould live of the Goſpel,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. which <hi>Divine right</hi> all faithful Miniſters who labour in the Word and Doctrine, may with juſtice, honour, and good Conſcience, both require and enjoy, without any reproach of Idleneſs, Covetouſneſs or oppreſſion: And Chriſtian people not onely may in courteſie, but ought in equity and duty to provide, what is honeſt, comely, and competent for them, as God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained: hereby expreſſing the fruits of their faith and love, their ſenſe of juſtice, and gratitude both to God and man; their value of the Goſpel, and <hi>ſpirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good things,</hi> their <hi>taſte</hi> of the <hi>heavenly</hi> gift and treaſure; their zeal for the worſhip of God, and for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124892:6"/> honour and ſervice of Chriſt, in his Evangelical and eternal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>6</label> So that, as it is a ſin in any true Miniſter not to <hi>diſpence faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> the myſteries of the Goſpel to his flock or people, over <hi>whom the Lord hath ſet him,</hi> for which neglect a <hi>wo and curſe</hi> lyes upon his ſoul:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.16.</note> In like manner it muſt needs be a great ſin and ſhame in Chriſtians (full of impiety, <hi>injuſtice,</hi> and high <hi>ingratitude</hi> both to God and man) not to diſcharge this duty and debt, by provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a competent and <hi>comfortable</hi> maintenance for the faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.17.</note> either ſuch as onely teach, or both teach and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern well, as good Shepherds of the flock of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For which duty there are ſo many <hi>clear</hi> and moſt convincing grounds of equity, alledged by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> And to theſe is added ſuch expreſſe Declarations of the <hi>will</hi> of God, both in the Law,<note place="margin">Numb. 18.23.</note> under the <hi>Levitical Miniſtry,</hi> and in the Parallel Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the <hi>Evangelical:</hi> Againſt both which pregnant grounds of <hi>Miniſters maintenance,</hi> who ſo liſts to cavill or blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, he merits no reply, any more than <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> did from <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> or <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> from <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the firſt Quere, reſolving it into this <hi>Affirmative.</hi> That ſince the Lord hath appointed ſome men by office and duty to celebrate holy miniſtrations in order to ſet forth the glory of God in his mercy, and the love of Chriſt in his ſufferings, that men might beleeve and repent to the ſaving of their ſouls; it muſt needs follow by the proportion of Gods love and care for the Miniſters; That the competent and comely maintenance of theſe Evangelical Miniſters, (as the ſervants of the Lord for the Churches good) at other mens coſts and charges (in caſe they require it) is not onely by neceſſary conſequences to be gathered out of, but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in expreſſe terms commanded in the Word of God, which ſets forth the will of God in this caſe; not onely as a poſitive and <hi>temporary</hi> precept, but as grounded on eternal and indiſpenſible principles of piety, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and gratitude, which hold as firm in the New Teſtament, as in the Old; and intend as well the maintenance of thoſe that preach the Goſpel, as it did of thoſe that ſerved at the Altar.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere </seg>2</label> The ſecond Quere upon the account of Conſcience, is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lord hath any where in his Word (Old or New Teſtament) either expreſly or by good conſequence forbidden Miniſters of the Goſpel to receive, and Chriſtian people, as ſuch, to give to them as maintenance, either occaſionally by private bounty, of fixedly by publick donation, a Tithe or Tenth of any goods increaſe, as a part or portion meerly <hi>Typical, Judaical,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> appropriated to the <hi>Levitical</hi> Miniſtry, or Prieſthood, which by the coming of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124892:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſt is changed, and ſo aboliſhed; that <hi>Tithes</hi> may no more now be uſed by Chriſtians, either Miniſters or people, than <hi>Sacrifices</hi> or <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> To this the Anſwer is <hi>Negative;</hi> Nothing in the word of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears forbidding Chriſtians by private or publicks bounty to ſet a part a Tenth of their increaſe or ſubſtance to the glory of God, for the Maintenance of Piety or Charity, (both which ends the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Goſpel chiefly aymes at.) I ſay, no more, than it is forbiden or commanded to give any other portion above or below the Tenth. Certainely, if Chriſtians may lawfully devote a 5, 6, 9, or a 12, 15, 20. part to the glory of God in a publick good, no reaſon or Religion can be produced againſt the Tenth as the only unlawful portion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If any portion or quantity as a fit <hi>Medium</hi> between Miniſters merit &amp; peoples retribution be ſpecified, intimated, recommended or ordeined by God in the Goſpel, ſure it is no other, but this of Tithe or tenth, as I ſhall afterwards prove in the 3. <hi>Quere.</hi> If none be pointed out or ſignified, as Gods choice, then is any one lawful, which is fit; and that moſt lawful, which is fitteſt to attain Gods end: which is evidently commanded; namely, the <hi>competent maintenance of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> under the Goſpel, at a rate anſwerable to that which thoſe enjoyed under the Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſcruple ſome make of Tithes as <hi>Jewiſh;</hi> urging that place, that ſince the Prieſthood is changed, the Law muſt bee changed;<note place="margin">Hebr. 7.12.</note> and therefore no tithes are allowed to the Evangelical Miniſtry, is eaſily anſwered.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>1</label> 1. It ſavours too much of the Jews covetous &amp; hard hart, to queſtion, whether a Chriſtian may not be as grateful to his Miniſter, as a Jew was to his Prieſt: of which there is no doubt. And it argues too much of a Jewiſh confidence &amp; preſumption, to think, that the Lord ſhould ſo far prefer the Altar miniſtry before that of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Numb. 18.21. Levit. 27.30. Gen. 14.20. Gen. 28.22. <hi>Plut. in Lucul. Diodo. Sic</hi> l. 5. c. 2. <hi>Macrob. Satur.</hi> l. 3. c. 12. <hi>Majores ſolitos decimam Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi vovere, è Varrone. Plin. Hiſt. Nat.</hi> l. 12. c. 14 <hi>Herod.</hi> 1. <hi>Clio. Livi Dec.</hi> 1. l. 3</note> as to provide certain and ample Maintenance for the firſt, and none for the ſecond. As if there were more excellency in a beaſt ſacrificed, then in Chriſt crucified.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>2</label> 2. The Divine <hi>appointment of Tithes</hi> to be payd, as Gods portion, among the Jews to his Prieſts, doth not argue any thing ſo much as this; that they are Gods ſtill after the Law, as they were his in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious right before the Law, when <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> received them, as a right of <hi>Abram,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> vowed them as a due to God; from which ancient light of tradition and uſe among the Holy Patriarcks, the opinion which many of the Heathens had touching the holineſs of a tenth part of their goods and ſpoils aroſe; which they in many places conſecrated as due to their Gods, <hi>Jupiter, Hercules</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:124892:7"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>3</label> 3. It doth not follow by any right reaſon, that what ever the Jews uſed to Religious ends, was therefore Ceremonial, Typical, and to be aboliſhed; There was never any thing in Tithes diſcovered as a Shadow, Type, or Ceremony; They were uſed long before <hi>Moſes:</hi> the inſtitution and end of them in all times depended meerly upon common grounds of Piety, Equity, and Gratitude, both to God and man; The moſt wiſe and juſt will of God was pleaſed to accept firſt from the Patriarck, and afterward to claim as his own. <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30. then to aſſigne that <hi>quantum, or portion</hi> of Tenths for his publick ſervice, and the ſuſtenance of thoſe men who were imploied in it. Now ſince the ſame ends, as to the main, are ſtill required by the Lord, namely, the Maintenance of his publick Miniſtry under the Goſpel, there is no reaſon, why <hi>Tithes</hi> as a proportionate means, ſhould be aboliſhed. Since there is ſtill an Evangelical Prieſthood and <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> ordeined by God, and derived from Chriſt; which men (needing Humane and Mortal ſupplys, as much as the <hi>Levites</hi> and Prieſts of old did) now exerciſe, celebrate and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; doubtleſs, as the ſame neceſſities now require like ſupplies; and a parallel livelyhood is by the Lord ordeined in the Goſpel; ſo nothing hinders, but theſe may bee made by the ſame meaſure of <hi>tenths,</hi> upon the ſame grounds of equity which were valid among the Jews; Eſpecially, conſidering the Miniſtry of the Goſpel is more <hi>paineful,</hi> more <hi>honorable,</hi> and not leſſe uſeful, than that of old was; Nor is it to bee preſumed, that God ſhould be more ſtrait handed to this Miniſtry, which hath the honor to be in Chriſts ſtead, the Lord of glory: the beloved Son of God.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>4</label> 4. It is moſt certain, that the ſame moral tyes and dutys he now upon Chriſtians, which did upon the Jews, in matters of Piety, Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Charity; yea and thoſe Patternes of <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> in Church or State, which were uſed by them, are ſo far allowed, and by Gods pattern recommended as beſt to Chriſtians, according as they wiſely conſider the fitnes of them, as means to thoſe <hi>holy ends</hi> which the Lord ſtill requires. The ſanctifying of a Sabbath or day of reſt; Confeſſing of ſins over the ſacrifice; reading and hearing the Law and Prophets explained; Praying to, and praiſing of God; Charity to the poor; Relief of enemies in diſtreſs; Reconciling before they come to the Altar with their gift; preparation before the Paſſover, &amp;c. So alſo as to other Lawes, Judicial, Penal, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical, (which the Jews had and obſerved by a poſitive command of God) Chriſtians may, under a different miniſtration and form, uſe and do the ſame things, upon thoſe moral and general grounds of Equity, Piety, and Charity, which are ſtill, and ever will bee in force, as they are in this point of <hi>Miniſters maintenance</hi> by <hi>Tithes,</hi> as well, yea better than an any other way.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:124892:7"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>5</label> 5. What ſober and judicious Chriſtian underſtands not this clearTruth? That where any duty is at large, <hi>or in general,</hi> commanded by the Lord, the ſame duty in its particular circumſtances, qualifications, and reſtrictions, (which humane prudence, according to the liberty granted, puts upon it,) is alſo commanded, approved and accepted: and ſo becomes not onely lawful, but neceſſary in its due time and proportions; Not abſolutely, poſitively and explicitely, as to every particular regulation and circumſtance, but relatively, conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, and incluſively: where, the duties of preaching, praying, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>receiving, diſtributing, paying tribute, reliefe of Parents, honoring God</hi> with <hi>our ſubſtance,</hi> &amp;c. are commanded, without any limitations, as <hi>who, when, where,</hi> how <hi>long,</hi> how <hi>much,</hi> by <hi>whom,</hi> to <hi>whom,</hi> &amp;c. In theſe caſes, not only the duty in the abſtract and general, by expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite precept is injoined; but alſo, in the <hi>conorete,</hi> as it is bounded with convenient circumſtances and proportions, fitted to the main end.</p>
            <p>The like <hi>juſtifiableneſs</hi> is moſt clear in this portion of Tithes, to be aſſigned to Miniſters for their maintenance; for which we have not onely the general Ordinance, and command of God often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the New Teſtament (as I have ſhewed) which always in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the fitteſt means for it; but we have alſo Gods wiſdome and bounty, particularly pointing us, even ſo as of old, to that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he choſe as his, and gave to his Miniſters, from which we have no command to vary or alter; but rather an injunction or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ordinance to continue, ſince it is ſtill a means no leſſe ſutable to the main end then it was before; and as neceſſary for the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the evangelicall Miniſtry, as it was for the Levitical.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>6</label> 6. As for the <hi>change of the Law,</hi> which (is objected) muſt follow <hi>the change of the Prieſthood;</hi> it is fulfilled moſt clearly, not by taking away <hi>Tithes,</hi> or utter aboliſhing the payment and uſe of them in the Church, but by the transferring of them to another Prieſthood and Miniſtry, which is not after the <hi>Aaronical,</hi> and <hi>Levitical,</hi> but after the <hi>Melchiſedecian</hi> and Chriſtian order and ſucceſſion; with nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which, the paying or receiving of Tithes, as an honour to Chriſt, and a maintenance of his worſhip, are any way inconſiſtent, as the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> proves, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.8. but rather moſt congruous; as a token of honour to Chriſts royal and eternal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; and a teſtimony of gratitude and devotion, from thoſe that worſhip him.</p>
            <p>In which point even of Tythes, the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urges, the Prerogative or eminency of right and claim, which Chriſt hath for ever, both to the honour of the Prieſthood, and conſequently to Tithes, as properly belonging to him, which was long before the <hi>Levitical</hi> Inſtitution, foreſhewed in that great
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:124892:8"/> Type of Chriſt, <hi>Melchiſedeck;</hi> who bringing forth Bread and Wine, the Symbols of Chriſts body and blood in the great Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Euchariſt, received in the perſon and right of Chriſt, Tithes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the faithful; yea and in ſome ſort, of <hi>Levi,</hi> as by an higher and ancienter right, which ſufficiently juſtifies, (if it do not implicitely command) any of <hi>Abrahams</hi> children af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the faith, by their paying of Tithes, to own with this honour and homage the royal Prieſthood of Chriſt, as by a tribute and an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering which he receives by his Miniſters, who are in his Name and ſtead miniſtring holy things now under the Goſpel, by whom (and no otherways) he <hi>which liveth for ever,</hi> now <hi>receiveth Tithes,</hi> as was prophetically prefigured of him; who yet while he lived on earth, received none in Perſon, becauſe the Levitical Miniſtry and diſpenſation was not yet finiſhed; of which Tribe the Lord Jeſus was not: Nor did the Apoſtolical wiſdome and tenderneſs require of the beleeving Jews any Tenths, while yet the Levitical ſervice, Altar and Temple were living (neither dead, nor deadly) leſt the Goſpel might ſeem a burthen to thoſe that were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe charged, and yet they were very gratefull to the Apoſtles; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſelling their eſtates, and laying the price at the Apoſtles feet.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>7</label> 7. As then the Lord Jeſus Chriſt did not aboliſh all <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> or Prieſtly office, and Miniſtry; but onely he changed the <hi>Aaroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> line, order, and Ceremony of Succeſſion; himſelf continuing a King and <hi>Prieſt</hi> for ever after the order of <hi>Melchiſedeck;</hi> ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may he be thought utterly to have aboliſhed thoſe ancient Prieſtly rights to Tithes uſed before and under the Law, as a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſtill of his Miniſters, and an agnition of his Soveraign Prieſthood; however he hath changed the temporary and interve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which aſſigned them to the Levitical Miniſtry: The channel or courſe is changed, but not the ſtream, which is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned another way, end derived to another ciſtern. Nothing then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids Chriſtians (now under the Goſpel) to own this duty to Chriſt, and diſcharge it even in a way of <hi>Tithes,</hi> dedicating them to his honour and ſervice in the maintenance of his Miniſters, by whom Chriſt as our High Prieſt, ſtill inſtructeth, prayeth for, and bleſſeth his people.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I affirm, There is ſo little, ſo nothing, in the <hi>Analogy,</hi> and <hi>Tenor,</hi> or in the Letter of the New Teſtament againſt Miniſters of the Goſpel being maintained by this portion of Tithes; that there is much more preponderancy to prove them not onely lawful (which is evident) but (for the moſt part) neceſſary, as a right and duty: yea to ingenuous Chriſtians, who are neither covetous, nor conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, they will appear the moſt laudable, wiſeſt, equalleſt, and fitteſt meaſure or <hi>dimenſum;</hi> 1. As a due which God challengeth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:124892:8"/> to himſelf. 2. As an honorary right, ſpecially belonging to Chriſt in his Prieſtly dignity. 3. As a grateful retribution of beleevers to the divine bounty, of which they have received all, and to which they owe themſelves. 4. As an equitable valuation and requital of Chriſts Miniſters labour among them. 5. As an imitation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neereſt to Gods ancient command, and pattern under the Law, and to the devotion of his holy ſervants before the Law. 6. As the fruit of tender hearrs, carefull and conſcientiouſly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, leaſt they ſhould come ſhort any way of that which the Lord may juſtly expect from them; and which by one moſt pregnant place, ſeems ſo expreſly to require of them; which I ſhall urge in my Anſwer to the third Queſtion: Which here follows to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere </seg>3</label> The third <hi>Quaere</hi> is, Whether the Lord hath by any Evangelicall Precept, preciſely appointed any ſuch <hi>Quantum</hi> or <hi>meaſure,</hi> as a tenth portion of increaſe and profits to be exactly and conſtantly paid by Believers to their Miniſters; and theſe to be yearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by Miniſters as their due, for their livelihood or maintenance? Or what poſitive right, as from God, have Miniſters of the Goſpel, to plead for their <hi>Tithes</hi> here in <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> To this I muſt firſt Anſwer by diſtinguiſhing upon theſe terms, <hi>Right or Due,</hi> which may be taken in a twofold ſenſe, either as to a particular <hi>precept,</hi> explicitely <hi>exacting</hi> a Tenth in terms, as in the levitical Law; or as to a general Ordinance including, implying, and referring to a Tenth: We muſt diſtinguiſh between the <hi>letter</hi> of the Scripture, limiting to a Tenth, as in the Old Teſtament: And the ſcope, ſenſe, or equitable meaning of the Scripture, intimating or pointing to, and exemplarily recommending that proportion, in the New Teſtament, as the beſt and moſt proper means, where it is meet and proportionate to that end, which God hath expreſly ordained; Which is, that the <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel;</hi> even ſo <hi>as the Miniſter of the Altar, did of the Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein although particular circumſtances may differ, under dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>adminiſtrations;</hi> yet the main deſign and general intention is the ſame; both as to the end, <hi>competent maintenance;</hi> and to the apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt means, ſo far as they are in our power, and opportunity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But it is urged, if God required a Tenth under the Goſpel, why did he not in any place of the Goſpel mention that part by name, as of old he did?</p>
            <p>Gods ſilence in the New Teſtament, as to renewing a preciſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for paying Tithes by name, to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, is no abrogating of them, as to right and equity; the not ſpecifying or exacting of believers a Tenth, was upon ſeveral grounds of divine wiſdome; which are evident.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:124892:9"/>1. It was not neceſſary; becauſe the rule and meaſure of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, devotion and equitalble retributions (to which the Apoſtle 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. referr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Chriſtians under <hi>the Goſpel</hi>) as a continued binding ordinance of the Lord in this caſe, is ſufficiently ſet forth in the Old Teſtament, both by the Religious bounty of the Holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarcks, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> (expreſſed in this proportion of Tithes or Tenths, before the Law) And alſo by the expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, afterward pitching upon this <hi>quantum</hi> as his, and appointing it for the fitteſt medium, which his wiſdome and bounty thought good to ſet between the <hi>covetouſneſs of Prieſts,</hi> who might have exacted or expected more; and the <hi>niggardlineſs of people,</hi> who might have allowed leſs, if left to their own arbitration, choice, &amp; free will; (men being naturally <hi>penurious</hi> to the true God and his word, as having no love to, or delight in his ſervice; and only prodigal to their own <hi>Idolatrous fancies,</hi> as thoſe which they moſt count and eſteem: Charets and Horſes ſhall be dedicated to the Sun, or the Queen of Heaven; when a Lamb, or Pigeon, a little meal or cake is grudged as an offering to the true God and holy Temple. The equity and analogy of Gods former will, continues in force, and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently binds the conſcience to obed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, although a particular precept were not renewed; eſpecially, where Chriſtians are ſpecially referred to that: which is clearer in this point of Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by Tithes, than for the Lords daies <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or Reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The indulgence of God foreſaw, and the Apoſtles tendernes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, That an exact or ſtrict requiring or mentioning of the Tenths of all increaſe, and profits to bee payed to the Miniſters of the Goſpel in all places, and at all times, might diſcourage Jews and Gentiles from the Goſpel; yea, and many times prove very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to Chriſtians; who muſt expect perſecution; to whom it might have been a burthen and ſnare in their uncertainties, diſtreſſes, and poverty. A burthen, to pay alwaies a tenth of their profits, hardly gotten, and hardly preſerved: A ſnare alſo, if they payed them not exactly. Yet this Indulgence, Silence, Remiſſion, which in the primitive tenderneſs might bee permitted by the Lord, is no abrogation of the duty or Law; any more than the omiſſion of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion for forty years in the wilderneſs, was a vacating of that ordinance of God to the Jews; or the not commanding expreſly the Lords day to bee kept as a Sabbath, is any argument againſt our ſanctification of it, which is only related in the New Teſtament as a primitive practice.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the Lords not mentioning Tithes in the very terme (or <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntum</hi>) ſomthing ſeems left in the Goſpel to the conſcience and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, both of people and of Miniſters: Theſe, that they may in part remit in times of diſtreſs thoſe rights, as <hi>Paul</hi> did: not exacting this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124892:9"/> proportion of Tenths; which they might otherwiſe claime &amp; expect as due: People alſo by ſo much Indulgence are invited to ſhew ſo much the more, a liberal and a willing mind where God enables them; either occaſionally to return; or conſtantly to ſettle even ſuch a <hi>maintenance</hi> on their Miniſters; as comes neereſt both to the equity of Gods will: and the exemplarines of that proportion of Tithes, which he anciently required as his own, <hi>and which we do not find</hi> he hath in the <hi>Gospel remitted;</hi> for then the Lord had left his Miniſters of the Goſpel to meer uncertainties and benevolence, which was not <hi>even ſo</hi> as he ordeined for thoſe of the Altar; and indeed flatly contradicts the Apoſtles reddition, <hi>Even ſo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Divine wiſdom ſaw that in ſome conditions of Chriſtians living, a Tenth of the earths yearly increaſe would not afford a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, or any convenient maintenance for Miniſters; as in Cities, and populous Towns; ſo in Caſtles, Ships, &amp;c. There ſome other way, by rents of Houſes, or Trades increaſe, muſt equivalently be raiſed. And here although men now a daies would grudg to pay a tenth of Trades increaſe or their callings, yet we read of old it was payd by many Citizens, Merchants, Lawyers and Phyſicians.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Although we do not find in the Practice of primitive Churches, among Jews or Gentiles, mentioned in the New Teſtament, that either the Apoſtles or other Paſtors and Miniſters alwaies uſed this power, or ſtrictly required the juſt proportion of a Tenth; which to the beleving Jews (on whom the Charges due to the Altar ſtill lay for a time) might have ſeemed a burthen; and ſo to the Gentiles, among whom not many rich or Noble, but poor and mean people in Cities chiefly received the Goſpel, and this oft with perſecution: Yet we find in thoſe daies, in ſtead of exact Tithes and ſetled mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that which is not in theſe daies to bee expected: Namely,<note place="margin">Acts 2.45.</note> That in thoſe primitive times Chriſtians were willing to ſell all, or great part of their poſſeſſions, to bring the price of them and lay it at the Apoſtles feet, for their ſupport, and the Churches relief; So fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did they, as then, ſo afterward exceed the proportion of a tenth part, that many gave all they had and themſelves too, to ſerve the Lord and his Church.</p>
            <p>Thoſe were excuſable in their poverty and perſecution, if they had come ſhort of a tenth; and were commendable where they moſt what exceeded it. Wiſdome teacheth us, that neceſſity diſpenſeth with poſitive precepts; that different times requires different counſels and wayes; yet alwayes keeping neereſt to Gods rule, and aiming at the ſame good end.</p>
            <p>Thoſe were the pureſt flames of Chriſtians firſt Love, and Primitive Zeal; when Apoſtles, and other excellent Miniſters of the Goſpel, were received as the Angels of God; the feet of thoſe Meſſenge s
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124892:10"/> of peace were beautiful; Their perſons dearer to believers then their right eies; The honor of their calling and Miniſtry daily kept up with frequent miracles; that the poverty of <hi>S. Peter (Acts</hi> 3 6.) when he had <hi>not gold or ſilver,</hi> was venerable, by the miraculous power hee exerted to the creple, in relieving him beyond his deſire; and it was alſo formidable, in the dreadfull ſentence hee thundred againſt the ſacrilegious parſimony, lying, and diſtruſt of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira.</hi> Tithes need not to be urged or exacted <hi>then when Chriſtians</hi> are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward beyond what they were able; and in the midſt of poverty abounded to a liberality.</p>
            <p>But alas! wee are now ſunk to the dregs of time; raked up and buried in the very aſhes or embers of devotion; All is become worſe and more perilous, by how much it drawes more of the <hi>later dayes;</hi> when the charity of <hi>men ſhall grow cold; iniquity abound:</hi> when men <hi>ſhall be lovers</hi> of <hi>themſelves, of the World and Mammon, more then of God:</hi> Generally ſeeking <hi>their own</hi> profits, and preferments, and not <hi>the things of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, and his Church; when miſerable forms of <hi>penurious Piety,</hi> and ſacrilegious ſanctity, ſhall eat out and deny the power of Godlineſs; when men ſhall chuſe to ſerve God in away that <hi>coſts them nothing, turning Godlineſs into gain;</hi> when the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, the more learned, holy, able and faithfull they are, are forced to hide their faces, and are covered with that confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, both from poverty and reproach, which ſome men delight to caſt upon them; The more beautiful their wings and feet are, which ſhine with <hi>the beams</hi> of the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs,</hi> his truth and his ſpirit, the more they are forced to lie among the pots, to bee levelled to, and buried among <hi>the meaneſt of</hi> the people; Having enough to do to preſerve now their own eies from being pulled out by thoſe unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men, (ingrateful Ravens) who neither regard <hi>the Mother</hi> which bare them, <hi>nor the Father</hi> which begat them.</p>
            <p>So that different minds and manners of Chriſtians may will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire different ways and ſetling of maintenance for Miniſters; The more covetous, ingrate, and inconſtant people are, the more needful it is, and more required by God, that competent and conſtant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion ſhould in conſcience be urged, and in prudence eſtabliſhed for his Miniſters of the Goſpel. It was pious in primitive times, for Chriſtians to pay no Tithes, when they failed not to give much more. It is impious now not to pay Tithes, when theſe are all that is ſettled or may be expected for maintenance, and hardly this obtained: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore priſtine Liberality, and Miniſters ſhall gain by taking no Tithes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We find in all ages of the Church, either in the intervals, or ceſſations of perſecution, (when peace, proſperity and plenty, had ſomewhat ſlackned, as the Sun doth ſhining upon fire, the warmth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:124892:10"/> of piety) that the devouteſt Chriſtians in all places, not onely gave free-will offerings and oblations, but even the <hi>Tenth or Tithes</hi> of their profits and and increaſe both <hi>perſonall and prediall;</hi> out of which the Biſhops, and Presbyters, the poor, and other pious uſes were maintained: And this out of not onely cuſtome, and bounty, but of conſcience, thankfulneſſe, and duty;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ig.</hi> Hom. in Num. 11. Cypt. ep. 66. J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron. in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 3. Aug. ſer. de Temp.</note> as coming up to that proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they ſaw God of old required, and to which in the New-Teſtament he referred them. As <hi>Origen,</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> St. <hi>Jeronimus Auſtin</hi> and others of the Ancients teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Which Catholick conſcienicous cuſtomes among Chriſtians, of paying Tithes to the Miniſters of Chriſt, came afterward to be ſetled, by particular gifts or donations. And at length, in the abating of Chriſtians fervour and bounty, Tithes were eſtabliſhed, by Edicts <hi>Imperial, Canons</hi> of <hi>Councels</hi> Eccleſiaſtical, &amp; alſo by particular <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws</hi> or Statutes in every country; which included the donation, conſent and frewil of all Eſtates and degrees ſeverally and jointly, who were, as Proprieters of Lands and Eſtates, related to and included in any Chriſtian Polity or community.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To anſwer then that Queſtion; what Poſitive Right, as from God or man, have Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> to their Tithes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There clearly appears (without any violence to Scripture or reaſon) a fivefold right which miniſters of the Goſpel in <hi>England</hi> juſtly plead to their maintenance by Tithes, as here ſetled in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That right of <hi>Natural Equity</hi> and grateful retribution, which every mans own conſcience dictates; which God, who hath implanted it in them, requires of them; and which the Apoſtle, by many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in Souldiers, Shepherds, and husbandmen preſſes 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. ariſing from the merit of Miniſters labours in the Church, of which God is the juſteſt valuer, by which they deſerve to live of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> ſo as becomes the Goſpel: i. e. the God and Saviour there ſet forth. And ſo as muſt be anſwerable to what their Studies, Pains and Places do require: The Labourer hath Gods right to his wages: which ought to be, not what a <hi>Nabal</hi> will give; but what his time, care and pains in juſtice deſerve: The <hi>light of Nature</hi> taught all men to value the ſervice of their Prieſts at an high and honorable rate. None ever grew ſo mean and niggardly as ſome that pretend to be reformers, but cannot tel where to ſix, till al is waſted and deformed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Miniſters of the Goſpel have a Scriptural Right, drawn from the will of God, expreſly ordaining, as I have ſhewed, a <hi>livelyhood in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral;</hi> and a <hi>power</hi> of partaking of other mens temporal good things; And although the Lord in the Goſpel hath not by renewed precept ſo expreſly confined it to this particular proportion of Tenths by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>mes and in terms; yet he hath expreſly commended to Chriſtians imitation the equity of the old Law; &amp; referred them to the exemplary
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:124892:11"/> benignity of Gods love, bounty, and care toward his Miniſters at the Altar, to whom he aſſigned his own portion, the Tenth, binding Chriſtians incluſively and relatively, in Conſcience, yea leaving them without excuſe (in like caſes) if they do not eſtimate Miniſters la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as highly, or provide for them, <hi>Even ſo, as he hath ordained;</hi> equivalent, parallel, or proportionate, both in competency and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>
               </label> For this is clear, that the Lord hath given to Beleevers, evident Rules of religious gratitude, and Examples of holy retributions; not according to mans good pleaſure, but Gods; not as a benevolence of good will, but as a retribution of righteouſneſs and duty; which are ſet forth, 1. In the piety and devotion of the <hi>Patriarchs of old,</hi> who (no doubt) had this meaſure of a Tenth to be offered to God; from that traditional Theology, which their Forefathers taught them, by words and works; as a beam of Gods wiſdome; who indulging to ſinful man nine parts, (when indeed he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited all) reſerved to his particular honour and ſervice a <hi>tenth:</hi> 2. We ſee the Lord challengeth this Tenth among the Jews as his own; not only by right of creation and donation, for ſo all is his; but alſo by a peculiar and religious claim; that man might teſtifie by paying a Tenth to the Lord, that he owns and adores him as the giver of all; and that by this Tenth portion men might have the benefit, as God the honour, of religious publike ſervice. 3. This portion or peculiar reſerve of the Lord to himſelf, we find he did afterward fully aſſign and give to the Levitical Miniſtry at the Altar, as a fit proportion to maintain them, and to keep up the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Majeſty of his ſervice. 4. Both before the Levitical Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or Miniſtry; as alſo after it was finiſhed and changed by Chriſt, we read, Tithes not onely preſented to Chriſt as honorary, in his Type <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> in the Hiſtory of the Old Teſtament; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo challenged in the New, as a due or right belonging to Chriſt, in order to ſet forth the honour and prerogative of his royall and <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Prieſthood;</hi> that not onely he had this right before <hi>Levi</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> but alſo beyond them, and upon them; whoſe Prieſthood ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, after Chriſts appeared; and they ought, as <hi>Levi</hi> did in <hi>Abraham,</hi> to pay Tithes to Chriſts Evangelical Miniſtry; who not dying any more, nor changing his Prieſthood or Miniſtry, hath a perpetual right to receive Tithes, as well from the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> by the Faith, as <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> had in his Type or Figure to require them of <hi>Abraham:</hi> And this ſo long as the viſible Miniſtry of Chriſt continues among men on earth; which he hath appointed to be carried on by men, is his Miniſters and Embaſſadors.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Scriptural right which Miniſters under the Goſpel have to Tithes, is yet more emphatically and induſtriouſly, upon ſerious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124892:11"/> ſet forth in that pregnant place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they who preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> Which words, ſince they are a concluſion drawn from many Premiſes, and do import not a counſell and advice of Apoſtolical prudence, but an Ordinance of God, an Evangelical <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> which binds the conſcience by the divine Authority of it; we muſt not ſuperficially, but ſeriouſly conſider the weight and force of it, which lyes thus:</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle intending to prove a right or lawful power (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which himſelf and all true Miniſters had to <hi>an honourable mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.6.</note> (however he might ſometimes in charity and prudence remit the uſe of it) having firſt premiſed the grounds of naturall equity and common juſtice to be ſhewed to man and beaſt, and the light of God in Nature, and in the Law; he at laſt brings forth the pattern of Gods own appointment for his <hi>Miniſters at the Altar,</hi> which was ſufficiently known to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to be in great part, as to the certainty of it, by thoſe <hi>Tithes of the Earths increaſe,</hi> which the Lord firſt challenged as his own peculiar; and after aſſigned them, as his right to his Miniſters at the Altar; which the Levites and Prieſts held, not by the will, pleaſure, and bounty of men, but by a tenure from God, a <hi>rent,</hi> which he charged upon all the Lands: Immediatly, without any reſtriction, leſſening or ſubduction, upon the whole matter, the Apoſtle ſubjoyns and peremptorily concludes, <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord ordained,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That which is the equity of Gods will, his divine pleaſure both for matter and manner, for quantity and quality, in point of Miniſters maintenance under the Goſpel, is there ſufficiently declared; you need go no further for Gods direction, both the end and means hold parallel to that former; it is ſtill <hi>Gods Miniſtry,</hi> and ſo hath his right to his portion; what he then ordained, he ſtill ordains, That even upon the ſame certainty and proportion, ſuch as preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel (as of duty, office, and authority,) ſhould live of the Goſpel; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a portion (at leaſt) of other mens increaſe or revenues, as the Lord formerly required, and ſtill doth, to himſelf as God, and to his ſon Chriſt, whom he hath annointed to be King and Prieſt now in his Church; whoſe Miniſtry and Miniſters muſt <hi>Even ſo, be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Even ſo,</hi> not as to all particulars, properly Levitical, which are ceaſed; namely the Sacrifices. and legall oblations: but ſo far as the Tenth of the fruits of the earth ſtill continues and holds good, to like holy ends, though under different miniſtrations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Even ſo,</hi> That the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould enjoy not leſs liberal, honourable, ſetled maintenance, than the Miniſters of the Altar had; not of courteſie given, but out of conſcience paid;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:124892:12"/> not of alms, but of equity; not neceſſitons, not arbitrary; but ample and permanent.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord ordeined: id eſt,</hi> The will of God in this point (foreſeeing the hardneſs and narrowneſs of men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hearts, which may happen under the Goſpel miniſtry tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Miniſters; hath in their behalf declared of old, and doth now by <hi>mee</hi> an Apoſtle of Chriſt, renew it as an Ordinance of God, enacted w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th Majeſty and Divine Authority: Shewing that as th Lord doth not expect that men will be better natured under the Goſpel, or more large hearted than before: And as the Lord hath not leſs care or regard of his Evangelical Miniſters, than of the <hi>Levitical;</hi> ſo that hee hath in no ſort left their maintenance now to thoſe <hi>looſe and general in d fferencies,</hi> liberties and confuſions, which the covetous hearts of men are pr one to fall into, in things of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, if they fal under their own will and choice, which in this caſe muſt not be ſuppoſed, that the Lord hath done; For that were not <hi>even ſo:</hi> but would differ, as much as the tenure of owners to their Lands or Revenues: and of poor men to their Charity or Alms:</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Even ſo:</hi> To come ſhort then of that proportion, ſo far as in Gods Providence and bounty it ſtill holds; Not to give to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as was given to the Miniſters at the Altar, is it not to violate Gods ordinance?</p>
            <p>Sure it is not fulfilling of any donors bountiful will and command; who bids you ſo give <hi>to a ſecond, as to the firſt:</hi> if, having by preciſe appointment, as of due, and neceſſity, given twenty Shillings to the former; you give only, as of Charity, and with brow or inſolency, but one Shilling, or Penny, or nothing at all (of that depoſited bounty) to the ſecond; To whom the Giver not only intends, but clearly commands ſhould bee done <hi>even ſo,</hi> as <hi>to the firſt:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord ordeined.)</hi> As if the Holy Apoſtle had ſaid: you as Chriſtians now under another, eaſier and more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Miniſtry, as to the outward charge and forme (though the ſame, as to the ſubſtance, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>) muſt not ſuffer covetous, or parſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious temptations to riſe in your hearts, as a <hi>root of bitterneſs;</hi> So as to fancy, that becauſe the former ſubject of that Law for <hi>mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by Tithes;</hi> Namely, the <hi>Levitical</hi> Miniſtry at the Altar is changed, and ceaſed; therefore the Equitable and Moral bond is abrogated. But though the letter ceaſeth to bind you, upon thoſe Rates and Charges to maintain an Altar Miniſtry; yet, as then, the Lord ordained an ingenuous, ample and permanent proviſion (part of which, by Tithes at leaſt, yet remains in your power,) ſo the <hi>juſtice of Gods</hi> will ſtill continues; and you are to follow <hi>that patern</hi> of his love and care for his Miniſters. which bind you to obſerve it, as far as the altered <hi>ſtate of Times and Things</hi> will bear: Though you <hi>offer not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:124892:12"/> ſacrifices;</hi> yet you have Lands and Eſtates, of which God claimes his portion a Tenth: and <hi>hath ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ined</hi> (as of old,) his Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould be maintained by it, or ſomething equivalent unto it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Even ſo:</hi> That is, you are not to expect any other <hi>new Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> ſpecifying, how much: The Lord hath ſhewed you what equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table proportion he hath ſet between Paſtors and People; That the one may know his charge or burthen; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther his wages or mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from the Lord; by which he hath ſet us a <hi>limit</hi> to covering on one ſide; or repining on the other; That Miniſters may not think themſelves injured, nor people oppreſſed.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Even ſo:</hi> That is, you are not leſs to <hi>value</hi> or requite <hi>your</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters under the Goſpel: nor pretend liberty for a cloak <hi>of covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and maliciouſneſs;</hi> as if, becauſe you have no new precept in the very Term exacting a Tenth, you did not know what <hi>portion</hi> to aſſigne to God and his Miniſters as theirs; and therefore will pay nothing; or only what you liſt.</p>
            <p>You may eaſily ſee the will of God, both general for maintenance; and particular how much: hee would have you (as in all Reaſon and Juſtice you ought) to treat with equal meaſures of gratitude and devout retributions his Miniſters of the Goſpel, as thoſe were at the Altar; And ſince, as to many things very chargeable, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, as ſacrifices and the like, you are eaſed; you cannot in ſhame but pay the remaining portion of Tithes, which may bee applyed now to Miniſters of the Goſpel, as they were to thoſe of the Altar, without any ſcruple or ſcandal ſince they are of things of natures pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, not of Ceremonial Inſtitution or uſe; of Gods conſtant bounty not of his <hi>Temporary dispoſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. From the ſtrength of this <hi>place,</hi> not with cavill illuded, but with conſcience conſidered, Truly I do not ſee, how any good Chriſtian, when God gives power and opportunity, can in conſcience find any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence or laxation from the ſtrictneſs of this <hi>ſimilitude,</hi> or parallel of <hi>Divine Ordinance, Even ſo:</hi> to entertain the Miniſters of the Goſpel (which are ſuch in the due order, ſucceſſion, and authority of that holy office) with that portion which the Lord hath aſſigned to them; or with ſome thing analogous, and equivalent thereto where the Tenth of the earths increaſe is not to be had, or is <hi>incompetent:</hi> as in Cities, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Nor may any remiſſions of this power and right to Tithes, (which the charity of Miniſters, or their prudence at any time doth grant, in obedience to Gods providence, or imitation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and other holy men.) theſe I ſay, may not be any foundation or Pillar, on which to ground any fraudulent and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cuſtomes; which make no conſcience if they can plead uſe, and preſcription, to <hi>rob God of his honour,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt of his homage,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:124892:13"/> Miniſters of their maintenance, and people of the means of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the more indulgence either God or his Miniſters do in ſome caſes allow, Chriſtians ſhould the more ſtudy to recompence in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times any defects; ſo as may beſt expreſs how free and munificent a Spirit they are guided by under the Goſpel, far from the evill eye, or withered hand of ſacrilegious thrift.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Nor will any Chriſtian, truly conſciencious, liſten to any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous ſhifts and cavilings which riſe from the hardneſs of mens hearts, and depravedneſs of times; either challenging a liberty where God hath granted none, or pretending that as a competency, which is ſhort of Gods ordained allowance; much leſſe will they go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by a <hi>crueller</hi> way of Sacriledg, wholly to take <hi>away Gods</hi> por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſubſtitute what they liſt in the <hi>place</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>All Pleas then againſt Tithes, (even as they here appear grounded on a divine Ordinance) either armed with power, or trimmed with art and ſophiſtry, ſeem to ariſe from looſe, or illiberal principles, and reſolve into theſe Concluſions: 1. <hi>That the tenth of increaſe, is too much for God, who gives all to them.</hi> 2. <hi>Too much for Chriſt, who hath given himſelf to dye for them.</hi> 3. <hi>Too much for Miniſters, whoſe labours and lives are ſpent for them.</hi> And 4. <hi>Too much to be laid out upon their ſouls eternal welfare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They chuſe rather to ſhark upon Gods tenth, then truſt him for a bleſſing,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.9.</note> or fear him for a curſe on the remainder; preferring a few pounds, or pence unjuſtly gotten, before the peace of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; which is onely then true, when a mans ways are neereſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the will of God, expreſſed in holy precepts and examples; beſides grounded on natural Principles of equity and gratitude to God and man; To which, both Teſtaments, Old and New, bear witneſs; as they evidently do in this point of Tithes. For which I have proved this ſecond Right as Scriptural and Divine.</p>
            <p>A third right or claim, which Miniſters of the Goſpel have to Tithes, is from that Catholick cuſtome anciently obſerved by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in all times and places of ſetled Churches, who failed not out of Conſcience guided by the Word, and confirmed by Primitive pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns (before the coercion of any Canon Law) to pay at leaſt a tenth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Am. Mar. l. 27. de Epiſ.</hi> Ditantur obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionti us matro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum. Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt vehiculis inſidentes, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectè ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiti, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivia eorum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales ſuperant menſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> oft-times more, of their profits and increaſe to the Miniſters of the Church, for the ſupport of them and their families; alſo for thoſe other hoſpitable and charitable uſes, to which theſe employed their bounty.</p>
            <p>The great plenty of which is evident, by that luxury and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity wherein ſome Churchmen lived in the days of <hi>Ammiaenus Marcelliaus,</hi> a grave Heathen, and learned, for a Souldier, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtates days (<hi>Cent.</hi> 4.) tels us, <hi>That ſome Biſhops equalled, and oft exceeded the ſumptuouſneſs &amp; magnificence of Princes;</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:124892:13"/>
            <p>S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> alſo complains,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auſt. Serm. de Temp. 219. Hom. 48.</hi> Quia diſceſſit devotio, Dei acceſſit indictio fiſci. Dabis impio militi, quod non dabis ſacerdoti.</note> that the covetous coldneſs of ſome Chriſtians in his time, perſwading them to rob God, and to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw part of his portion, Tithes, from the Miniſters and poor, was a grand preſage of warrs and calamities coming upon them in <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> (as indeed they did ſoon after;) when the hand of violence would <hi>revenge</hi> the injury of Sacrilegious avarice; Either the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers rapine, (ſaith he) or the Exchequers confiſcation, will take what was grudged to Chriſt and his Church.</p>
            <p>Since then, moſt of our beſt Laws ſprang from the root of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes,</hi> and are daily more confirmed by that authority which the uſe and conſent of wiſe men in many ages have given to them, which is always ſuppoſed to be grounded upon ſome <hi>potent</hi> reaſon, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may be now leſſe <hi>apparent;</hi> by which cuſtome many men hold their civill eſtates and rights; There can be no reaſon, that <hi>parſimonious cruelty</hi> ſhould over-rule and <hi>antiquate pious,</hi> and <hi>liberal Antiquity,</hi> in this point and right of Tithes; which in <hi>England,</hi> as in all Chriſtian Churches, hath obtained the force of a Law, by the long cuſtomes, and ſucceſſion of times; which the beſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans freely and cheerfully, yet conſcienciouſly obſerved, as that which they eſteemed to be agreeable to the will of God, as well as conform to the beſt examples of their forefathers.</p>
            <p>It is true, no guilding of Antiquity, or paint of Cuſtome can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend what is in its nature evill, or change it into good; but the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal verdict and approbation, both by judgment and practice of holy and wiſe men, given to that which is in it ſelf good and lawful, advanceth it by the antiquity and univerſality of a good cuſtome, to the ſacredneſs and venerableneſs of a Law; giving great aſſurance and confirmation to the conſciences and practiſes of ſober Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: ſetting it far above the deſpite and petulancy of Innovators, who are given to change; and as Muſhrooms, are but of yeſterday, either as to their perſons or opinions; againſt whom, as a grand prejudice and obſtruction,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.16</note> the bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> urgeth the <hi>cuſtome of the Churches,</hi> which were guided by the general ſpirit of wiſdome; enough to ſtay and ſatisfie wavering or ſcrupulous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in things, for which as they had not a preciſe or ſpecial com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God, yet they were no where forbidden; as this matter of Tithes is not.</p>
            <p n="4">4 A fourth right or claim which Miniſters have to Tithes here in <hi>England,</hi> is from that perſonal bounty and freewill of Chriſtians in this Nation, who if no divine rule and precedent had directed them to retribute. <hi>Even ſo much</hi> as their Tenths to Miniſters; (which no doubt in conſcience they had regard unto) yet, as proprietors of their lands and eſtates, they lawfully and commendably might, and effectually have ſo far <hi>honoured God with their ſubſtance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3 9.</note> as to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:124892:14"/> have devoted to his Miniſters, for a conſtant retribution of their labours, the Tenth of their profits or increaſe ariſing out of thoſe Lands and Eſtates. There is no Title leſſe diſputable, then that of <hi>free gift,</hi> (where there is no fraud, no infirmity of underſtanding, an undoubted power upon juſt and valuable conſiderations, and to a good end) ſuch as God not onely alloweth in general, but rather ſeemeth to require in particular; which is the caſe here exactly; and hereby is given the proprieters former right, not ſo much to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as to God himſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> have that right to Tithes, and other ſetled maintenance, which ariſeth from thoſe Political Laws or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſanctions, which upon mature deliberation, and with publique Counſel of all Eſtates have eſtabliſhed long ago, and oft confirmed as juſt and good, thoſe particular donations of Tithes made by any lords and owners, as no way <hi>prejudicial</hi> to the publique good, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for profit, ſafety, or honour; (to which it is confeſſed, all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate acts and Intereſts muſt yeeld; being fruſtrate and invalid, if inconſiſtent with a publique and general good of a Nation.) Theſe Laws of the Land, which are the reſults of publique wiſdome and juſtice, have declared Miniſters right to Tithes, every way pious, juſt and good. Yea, and do enable them in their ſeveral places and portions, even by ſecular power to vindicate theſe rights; both perſonally to receive them, and conſtantly to preſerve them for their ſucceſſors, as a maintenance every way both juſt and fit; which right, by the Laws of the Land, as learned Lawyers are beſt acquainted with; ſo I hope ſome of thoſe Gentlemen are ſo much lovers of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Miniſters, as to plead their cauſe, and ſo valiant as to appear friends to them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In the laſt place, I may further twiſt and ſtrengthen this <hi>fourfold cord</hi> of Miniſters right, (by natural Equity, Scriptural Ordinance, Perſonal donation, and publique Sanction, which is not eaſily bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken;) by that <hi>divine acceptation,</hi> or <hi>appropriation,</hi> whereby God himſelf, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt are inveſted into a right; theſe joyntly as one God claim a property, and challenge as their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and due, what is once thus by any man, or men, dedicated to their ſervice, according as they have inſtituted in the Word. What is given to Chriſts Prophets and Miniſters in his Name, is given to God, ſo that it is now,<note place="margin">Acts 5.4.</note> (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> told <hi>Ananias</hi>) no more any private mans own, nor in his power; ſave onely in order to thoſe ends, and uſes, for which the Lord hath accepted it; and which he muſt be thought no leſs to approve in the particular obedience or devotion, then he doth command or require in the general precept or duty. Hence that complaint, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>Ye have robbed me, ſaith the Lord, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this whole Nation.</hi> For God is not onely well pleaſed with the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:124892:14"/> internal goodneſs and equity of his own will ind commands, but alſo with mans <hi>cheerful conformity</hi> to them, both in mind and manners; which is then moſt comfortable and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when it comes the neereſt unto that equitable rule, meaſure, and proportion, which the <hi>divine wiſdome</hi> hath ſet before men; which Tithes evidently are, when they are ſo paid to God, and ſetled for maintenance on Chriſts Miniſters, as leaves them no more to <hi>arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> and <hi>uncertain</hi> allowances, or <hi>niggardly ſtipends,</hi> then God did leave his <hi>Miniſters</hi> at the Altar; which is the preſcript or pattern to which the Lord refers Chriſtians; who are tyed to it, as to an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, ſtill in force under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I have done with this third <hi>Quaere,</hi> alſo, which I thus reſolve; That however there be not ſo immediate, preciſe, and explicite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for the exact <hi>Quantum</hi> of Tithes named in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; and however the Miniſters of the Goſpel do not claim a proper and immediate right to Tithes by the letter of the Leviticall Law; Yet they have by the dignity of their Miniſtry, and merit of their Labours, from the will of God in his Word, a general and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite right by way of equity and proportion; alſo a particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite title to Tithes, as they are devoted to God and ſetled upon his Miniſters here in <hi>England,</hi> both agreeable to, and grounded upon the equity of Gods ancient precept and example in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as alſo upon that expreſs <hi>Ordinance</hi> renewed and eſtabliſhed in the New, which carries a force of equivalency; and whatever proportion the nature of things may ſtill bear under the Goſpel, with thoſe under the Law; where eſtates in Lands and the increaſe of the earth are ſtill the ſame, and common to Chriſtians with the Jews. Herein then to imitate Gods Preſident cannot be <hi>unſafe,</hi> to come up to the proportion he required of old, cannot but be <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable;</hi> and every way to obſerve the neereſt conformity to his will, in the largeſt meaning and extent of that Ordinance in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament (<hi>Even ſo,</hi> &amp;c.) cannot but be moſt conſciencious and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, becauſe it hath leaſt of covetouſneſs or grudging.</p>
            <p>In caſes any way dubious, as to practice, it is ſafeſt for Chriſtians to be on the ſelf-denying ſide; and rather to propend to Gods inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt then to their own: They may ſin, as injurious and unthankful to God and his Miniſters; as diſhonouring and defrauding Chriſt of his rights and due, who do not pay the Tithes or Tenths; but they cannot ſin, who doubting between covetous and conſciencious ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, to what propotion the Lord under the Goſpel requires the grateful retributions of beleevers, conclude, by a juſt paying of their Tithes to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, to imitate at once Gods preſcript of old, and to fulfill the utmoſt, extent of his Ordinance in the New; referring to what ſtill continued of that ancient proviſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:124892:15"/> which chifley conſiſted in Tithes, as a conſtant maintenance.</p>
            <p>Since then, it is moſt evident, that a ſetled, competent main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for the Miniſtry of the Goſpel is as lawful now, as it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; and is no leſſe neceſſary now, then it was of old; and is as much deſerved now, and conſequently juſt, as of old; The ſureſt way for wiſe Chriſtians not to err on the right hand by Miniſters craving too much, (devouring <hi>whole houſes</hi> by pious inſinuations,) Nor yet on the left hand by peoples giving too little, is to take God for their <hi>umpire;</hi> and the <hi>pattern,</hi> his holy will, for the ſtandard of equity between Miniſters and people; that neither the flock may deny their Milk and Fleece, nor the Shepherd flea their skins, and devour their fleſh:</p>
            <p>Since the bounty of God beſtows on men the ten parts, and all they have (yea and offers Chriſt alſo to them) how can they (as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> urges it) in any generoſity, equity, or gratitude, grudg to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute one of ten to Gods glory, and their Saviours honour; who aſſigning this Tenth to their Miniſters maintenance, returns the bleſſing and benefit of it, to the good of mens ſouls, together with their families and neighbours; yea, and oft to the enlargment of their eſtates.</p>
            <p>If the Lord had not limited his portion to a <hi>tenth,</hi> godly men would hardly have contented themſelves, not to have given, with <hi>Zacheus,</hi> even half of their goods increaſe to God: The requiring but a Tenth, is not a burthen, but an Indulgence of God, in any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious mans eſteem.</p>
            <p>Thus have I anſwered theſe three <hi>Quaeries,</hi> raiſed from the firſt general ground of lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs; ſin or no ſin, in point of Conſcience regulated by the will and Word of God; From all which ſo clear reſolutions, I may firmly draw theſe concluſions:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That a compent, comely, and conſtant maintenance for the Miniſters of the Goſpel may lawfully and ought in Conſcience, to be raiſed out of other mens eſtates, by ſuch as have a right and power ſo to do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I conclude that Miniſters of the Goſpel may lawfully require ſuch maintenance, as Gods Ordinance, even by a Tenth portion of yeerly increaſe; and receive what is ſo raiſed or charged out of mens eſtates, without any ſin or ſhame; (however it be in ſome caſes comely and charitable in them to remit their right, yea and to preach the Goſpel <hi>gratis.</hi>)</p>
            <p n="3">3. I conclude, That neceſſitous, ſordid, and uncertain maintenance of Miniſters, is the ſin and ſhame of any Chriſtians, becauſe they are not provided for <hi>ſo as the Lord hath appointed,</hi> but ſhort of the Lords proviſion, which of old was at leaſt a Tenth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I conclude, although a Tenth or Tithe is not literally or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:124892:15"/> in terms concluded in the Goſpel, for reaſons beſt known to the wiſdom of God, in Primitive times. Yet this proportion is no where forbidden by the Lord: yea it is clearly included, ſpecially pointed unto, and exemplarily commended, as the beſt pattern and proportion to Chriſtians imitation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I conclude, That the private giving and publique confirmation or ſetling of Tithes, as part of Miniſters maintenance in <hi>England</hi> which the Law hath declared and ratified, beſide the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and cuſtome of the Nation for many hundreds of years, as the act and will of all Eſtates, is a very good work; (hardly to be amended or imitated in theſe days) full of noble and munificent piety; agreeable to the Word of God, both in the general and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and the equitable proportion ordained, to which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle referrs Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I conclude, That for any men by meer will and force to take away the publike maintenance by Lands and Tithes ſetled upon the Miniſters of the Goſpel, in order to the ſervice and worſhip of Chriſt, by the will and act of thoſe who had lawful power ſo to do; muſt needs be ſo far a ſin and ſnare of <hi>rapine</hi> and <hi>injuſtice,</hi> as by <hi>Law</hi> they belong to Miniſters in their ſeveral places; alſo a work of high and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous extortion, againſt the light of Nature, violating the <hi>will of the dead,</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, no man juſtly can do. Laſtly,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.15. Mal. 3.8. Rom. 2.22.</note> it is a ſin of <hi>Sacriledg or robbing God,</hi> to whoſe honour and ſervice they are ſet apart and dedicated, in a way agreeable to his will. Where the Donors, ſometimes the rightful owners of thoſe Lands, and the fruits of them, diveſting themſelves and their Succeſſors for ever, of any power of revocation, reſumption, or alienation, have inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Miniſters of the Goſpel and their Succeſſors, in the Name, and for the ſervice of Chriſt, with full poſſeſſion, and perpetual uſe of them; under many curſes and imprecations, and without any reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I conclude, That for any private Chriſtians who ſtands related to the ſociety and communion of this Nation, and is ſo bound by the Laws eſtabliſhed (which are the meaſure and ſtandard of civil juſtice, giving every man their due) to pay to the reſpective Miniſters of the Goſpel, ſuch portion of Tithes or profits, as are aſſigned them for maintenance; for any ſuch (I ſay) wilfully to defraud or deny the <hi>Miniſters</hi> their dues, or to encourage others ſo to do, can be no other <hi>then a fraudulent</hi> and injurious practice; no way conſiſtent with juſtice, divine or humane; contrary to all rules and examples of holy mens, piety, equity and charity; ſcandalous to the Goſpel, and reproachful to that grace of God,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>which teacheth men to deny all worldly luſts, and to live righteouſly, ſoberly, and holily in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:124892:16"/>8. Since it is moſt evident, that private and particular men in this Nation, either Landlords or Farmers, are as to Tithes they pay to Miniſters, not now the <hi>Proprietors or Donors,</hi> as of private good will and arbitrary bounty, but onely <hi>Truſtees, Executors,</hi> or payers of a publike debt, laid upon thoſe eſtates and lands which they now hold; Onely diſchargers of a <hi>ſacred truſt,</hi> or Feoffement, repoſed in them, by the will of God, and of their Forefathers, and of the Laws of the Land, (which include all Succeſſors Suffrages, and Conſent;) it follows, that they have no power in nature, Law, Reaſon, or Religion, to fruſtrate, revoke, or abrogate; nor yet to alienate, and pervert from the will and intent of the Donors, what hath been ſo ſacredly and ſolemnly ſetled: Nor have they cauſe, either to grudg at what Miniſters require, as their due; or to pay their Tithes with inſolency, or glorying in their bounty or gifts, which indeed is none of theirs, any more, then a Legacy is the liberality of the Executor.</p>
            <p n="9">9. I add in the laſt place, That where ſuch maintenance for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, is thus ſetled as in <hi>England,</hi> in order to Gods glory, and the peoples good; For any men <hi>illegally</hi> to deprive peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their lawfull Miniſters, or theſe of their <hi>lawful maintenance;</hi> for any man to challenge to himſelf <hi>this</hi> maintenance, who is no <hi>Miniſter</hi> in the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the Law; For any Miniſter to enjoy the benefit, who hath no lawfull civill right and title to it; yea for a lawfull Miniſter, lawfully poſſeſſed of right to the profits, yet not lawfully to diſcharge the <hi>duties</hi> of his place, according to his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; diligently taking care for the feeding that flock, of <hi>whoſe milk and fleece</hi> he partakes; each of theſe, I ſay, muſt needs be both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and man (reſpectively) guilty of the ſins of <hi>uſurpation, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, injurious intruſion,</hi> and <hi>ſacrilegious perverting</hi> that rule of righteouſneſs, which ought by all godly men to be ſtrictly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienciouſly obſerved, without any vain diſpenſations; neither inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding another mans office, rights or profits; nor fruſtrating, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feating the good ends of Gods appointment, and mans Law, by taking the benefit without doing the duty.</p>
            <p>And now Gentlemen, from theſe firſt conſiderations premiſed, and duely pondered with their Concluſions; I dare appeal to your judgments and Conſciences, Whether there be any ſuch Leproſie of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>irreligion,</hi> of <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt</hi> on the face of <hi>Tithes,</hi> as ſome men petend to be ſcared withall, which no Scripture diſcovers, no godly and learned man in in the Church of Chriſt, Ancient or Modern, ever perceived or ſuſpected; but ever approved that porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as moſt proper and convenient, becauſe neereſt to the pattern and mind of God?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:124892:16"/>2. Whether thoſe <hi>eager Petitions</hi> againſt Tithes, as <hi>unlawful, unjuſt, oppreſſive, unevangelical, abominable, &amp;c.</hi> either for Miniſters to receive them, or people to pay them, as maintenance, have any thing in them beſide their noiſe and cry; the repeated <hi>crambes</hi> of hard ſpeeches againſt <hi>Miniſters</hi> and their <hi>maintenance;</hi> alledging nothing of true Scripture grounds, or ſound inferences of right reaſon?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether thoſe <hi>Petitions</hi> againſt Tithes can in any truth or juſtice be eſteemed by wiſe and upright men, as the vote, ſenſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>moſt people</hi> in this Nation? and whether it be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to act againſt ſo clear mind of God, againſt the will of the dead, and the living too, in ſo great and publike an Intereſt; only upon the ſuggeſtions of a very few men compared to the whole? whether it be not an injury and indignity, to eſteem the moſt, and beſt of this Nation ſo ſimply ignorant, in ſo clear a caſe as this of Tithes is?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether the <hi>Scruples</hi> in <hi>Conſcience</hi> which ſome make againſt <hi>Tithes,</hi> (for which I have ſhewed ſo much reaſon, equity, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,) can by wiſe men be thought to have any other riſe but that of <hi>pitiful weakneſs,</hi> popular ignorance, vulgar prejudice, and prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous zeal at beſt? whether in others they carry not ſhrewd tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of <hi>malice, envy, covetouſneſs, and revenge?</hi> Laſtly, whether in ſome they may not be ſuſpected, as the ſmoke of the bottomleſs pit, to proceed from the <hi>depths, deviſes,</hi> and <hi>diſguiſes</hi> of Satan; from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, ſuperſtitious, or atheiſtical policies; projecting, by overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tithes, and all ſetled maintenance, to deſtroy all true Religion, Church, and Miniſtry, either as Chriſtian, or at leaſt, as reformed, in this Nation? Whether the breathings ſo fiercely againſt Tithes, do not threaten to make havock of <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Shepherd, Paſtors</hi> and <hi>People, Maintenance</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether, ſince it is ſo hard as to be next door to an impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to find or ſettle any other Baſis or fixed foundation whereon to ſettle a conſtant and competent maintenance upon Miniſters, ſave onely that of Lands and the fruits thereof; (for Taxes, Exciſe, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, or the like, as ſandy foundations, will never hold ſo many years, as this of Tithes hath done hundreds;) whether, I ſay, the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king theſe away without ſubſtituting ſomething better, or equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent at leaſt, in the room, doth not inevitably portend the overthrow of learning, and religion, civility, and Chriſtianity? which is the work not of reforming friends, but of deſtroying enemies.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether men truly conſciencious, have not much more cauſe to ſuſpect the taking away, or denying of Tithes to be a great ſin, then the paying and continuing of them? This hath ſo much of gratitude, of equity, of conformity to Gods holy will, of ſelf-denial,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:124892:17"/> that it cannot have any thing of evill in it; yea the beſt Chriſtians were ever moſt conſcienciouſly ſtrict in paying their Tithes: The other hath ſo much of unthankfulneſs, unholineſs, injuſtice, and ſelf-ſeeking, that it can hardly be a vertue, or among the things ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praiſe-worthy or comely. The Firſt hath much of God and Chriſt, the other of <hi>Mammon</hi> and <hi>Belial;</hi> nor can that Chriſtian be truly godly, who is in this point of ſo combined a duty, either care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to know, or unconſciencious to act according to Gods rule.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I leave to your conſideration, whether you have not more cauſe ſeriouſly to examine, and if you find the guilt of the ſin of Sacriledg upon this Nation, ſpeedily to expiate it by all poſſible care; wherever Gods portion, the Donors piety, and the Laws intention, in order to Gods glory, are made void, or perverted, either by injurious incroachments, hard cuſtomes, fraudulent compoſitions, or violent alienations of maintenance due to Miniſters, which make ſo many <hi>incompetent livings,</hi> that no able man can live comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably on them; but Miniſters are either by tenuity ſtarved or abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and peoples ſouls are deſtitute of the means of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>But I leave the Miniſters caſe in this point of their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which regards juſtice and Conſcience, to your more ſerious conſideration: againſt whom I ſhould, I fear, have ſinned, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, my own ſoul, and my brethren, if I had not endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, according to my Talent, to ſet forth to you and others ſo clear a light, both of reaſon, civil juſtice, and religion, as in this caſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears; enough to diſperſe, by Gods grace, all darkneſs of error, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, prejudice, or ignorance, which in this matter of Tithes may have poſſeſſed the minds of ſome men, who profeſſe to fear God.</p>
            <p>Having thus as briefly and clearly as I could ſet before you the firſt main conſideration,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 2. In prudence.</note> touching the lawfulneſs, or unlawfulneſſe of Tithes, in point of Conſcience. I crave your leave and patience to look to the ſecond, which regards not the matter, kind, meaſure, or proportion of them (which I have proved by Gods and mans laws to be good, lawful and moſt laudable,) but onely regards, what <hi>in prudence,</hi> is by ſome men pretended, for the better ordering and diſpoſing of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is hard to meet with every thing objected (as inconvenient) in the way of Miniſters maintenance by Tithes in <hi>England;</hi> which are propounded according to the various opinions men have of themſelves, heightned by their paſſions and intereſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some complain of thoſe <hi>Inconveniences</hi> which themſelves make: and the <hi>ſcandals</hi> which they lay in <hi>Miniſters</hi> way, by their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:124892:17"/> injurious cavillings, either deteining, or denying, what is many wayes their due. Others cry out of thoſe burthens and oppreſſions which themſelves leaſt feel, and moſt impoſe on poor Miniſters. Every one imagineth (as Empyricks do) that a great <hi>amendment</hi> will follow, if his adviſe bee followed; Not remembring, that remedyes partially and imprudently applyed, prove worſe then the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Many ears are open to hear the complaints made againſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and their maintenance; few are willing to hear Miniſters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt thoſe that <hi>injure and oppreſs</hi> them; In the firſt, ſecret hope of ſaving or gaining opens mens ears; in the ſecond, fear of coſt and charges ſhuts them; yea, and it is oft a fourth damage to a Miniſter, to ſeek to right himſelf by the Statute of <hi>treble damages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Not that in theſe things which are in the <hi>lower ſphear of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> I preſume to prejudg, interpoſe, or oppoſe your Counſels, Gentlemen: I know it is above my place and proportion; No one man may put his private thoughts into the balance againſt many, who adviſe or act as in a publick Sphear. I only preſent to you both ſides of thoſe Vulgar fancies and ſpecious propoſals, that you may ſee how <hi>counterfeit</hi> they are; though they be ſo <hi>currant,</hi> and highly cried up by thoſe, who take it ill, if all mens ſheaves do not bow down to theirs: whoſe fundamentall error uſually is, to conſider no mans thoughts but their own, and not thoſe very much; to think thoſe wayes moſt prudent, which are moſt popular; and moſt poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, which are moſt profitable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then, I may aſſert with truth and juſtice, againſt thoſe that are given to change the whole form &amp; way of Miniſters maintenance in <hi>England;</hi> That to make alterations without juſt and <hi>valuable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations;</hi> ſo to <hi>ſhuffle and confound</hi> the change, as thereby to make a prey and ſecular advantages by Miniſters loſs or leſſening in their maintenance, is but an <hi>unhandſome ſharking</hi> upon the Church of Chriſt; for it is not only the Miniſter and his family, that are thereby <hi>damnified,</hi> but the poor alſo, and the whole Pariſh or Congregation. Certainly, all ſacrilegious frauds and fetches, <hi>with Ananias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.4.</note> are but mockings of God, lyings againſt the holy Ghoſt, ſordid <hi>cheatings</hi> of a mans own conſcience for a little filthy <hi>Lucre:</hi> A very mean and poor ſpirited project, which will be pernicious to many worthy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: And is indeed every way <hi>unworthy,</hi> and far below the <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, munificence,</hi> honor and piety of <hi>this Nation:</hi> which hath been of old the liberal donor and faithful conſervator of Gods and his Miniſters portion for many hundred years. By which Patrimony
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:124892:18"/> of Religion, people had the ſpiritual, as Miniſters the temporal benefits.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To alter Miniſters maintenance, although upon juſt and <hi>equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent compenſations,</hi> yea and really to more <hi>conveniency</hi> for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and people; yet to do this without a fair hearing of all ſides; without and againſt the conſent of thoſe, many learned and worthy men, who are inveſted in the preſent <hi>right, poſſeſſion,</hi> and uſe; who are moſt neerly concerned in <hi>the buſineſs;</hi> This, I ſay, will ſeem hard meaſure, and is not like to give ſo general <hi>ſatisfaction;</hi> men are prone to ſuſpect and think themſelves injured, though you do them good, if againſt their wills: Suppoſing none can bee more <hi>faithful</hi> to their intereſts, then themſelves, or ſuch men (at leaſt) to whoſe wiſdome they dare commit the arbitration of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The grand project of men, <hi>Super-politick,</hi> and <hi>overwiſe,</hi> is this: Nothing will bee more prudent in order to publick Peace, than to bring all <hi>Tithes</hi> and <hi>Church Revenues</hi> into <hi>a civil tenure;</hi> To take the profits into a common purſe or <hi>exchecquer,</hi> from hence to diſpenſe them in ſuch convenient portions, as ſhall be thought fit; which Plot, pretends at once to caſe Miniſters of the truth, to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in, or compound for their Tithes, and will avoid all jangling ſuits and differences uſually attending.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is indeed a very plauſible pretenſion; which ſome men ſo pleaſe themſelves with, that probably, they have already layd out what place they ſhall get in this <hi>new Office.</hi> But to look deeper into it: I confeſs, it is a project of very great Worldly policy: but how <hi>Pious or Prudent</hi> it is, we ſhall ſee.</p>
            <p>It is indeed a very probable, if not, a neceſſary way to make <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> eyes, tongus, hearts and hands, <hi>dependent</hi> upon, and ſervient to the will of any men, that at any time obtain power and dominion; It will be a means to make alwayes a neceſſitous miniſtry; whoſe words will bee ſure to bee <hi>ſmooth, ſupple, and conform</hi> to any thing, that at any time power will command, or bounty reward. (Mens greateſt temptations lying in their ſtomacks, are extreamely ſharpned by fear of want, and feeling <hi>any neceſſities.</hi> What will not <hi>Jezebels proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts</hi> ſay or do, that are daily fed at her Table!</p>
            <p>By this means they that rule at any time, will bee ſure to have <hi>both ſwords (Temporal,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi>) at their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; a double <hi>Souldery</hi> or <hi>Militia;</hi> Secular, and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical; which laſt, ſhall every week in, every Pariſh, one day at leaſt be upon their guard and defence: moving all men, and perſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding them to be obedient, both for fear and for conſcience. This is the Wordly policy of this project.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:124892:18"/>2. But then in the eye of true <hi>wiſdome,</hi> this way appeares fully to ſuch as <hi>fear</hi> God, and chuſe rather to imitate his wiſe and holy exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; who would not have his Miniſters of the <hi>old,</hi> (and no more of the <hi>new Teſtament</hi>) to depend upon mens good will and pleaſure for their <hi>wages</hi> and <hi>reward;</hi> no nor to receive (as <hi>Philo Iudaeus</hi> obſervs) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and dues from the peoples hands, who were to bring them into the houſe of God, or the place he ſhould chuſe; and leave them there, leſt the Prieſts, as Gods more immediate ſervants ſhould fall under the ſhameful and diſhonourable burthens of flattery and ſervility; but live as Gods free men, who were to ſpeak his word in his name, whether men ſmiled or frowned; whether they did hear or forbear. Better a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt feed, as <hi>Micaiah,</hi> on the bread and water of affliction; or as the three Children on pulſe; or as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> on Locuſts, than they ſhould betray by <hi>ſecular</hi> and <hi>ſordid dependencies,</hi> the <hi>honour of God, the majeſty of his truth, the ſalvation of mens ſouls,</hi> by ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling either the truth, or truth ſpeaking, (with all ingenuous boldneſs and comely freedome) for a morſell of bread, or any greater gifts: which blind the eyes of the wiſe, and vaſſalate the of ſpirits the learned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Nothing will be more imprudent, more ignoble, more debaſing Miniſters and People, more detrimentall to learning and religion, more miſchievous to Church and State, to preſent time and poſterity, than <hi>venall</hi> and <hi>vaſſalated</hi> tongues of Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Further, Nothing juſt and vertuous, if oppreſſed, ſhall dare to be vindicated; and nothing vile or vicious, if proſperous, ſhall be blamed or reproved.</p>
            <p>A Miniſter of Chriſt ſhould ſpeak, as in <hi>his ſtead,</hi> as in the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God,</hi> as armed with <hi>Thunderbolts;</hi> not as charmed with <hi>morſels,</hi> or muzled with rewards. Alas! how eaſie (as we have ſeen by experience) will poor men (though Godly, though learned, though able; how much more, if they have any touch of mercenary ſoftneſs and weakneſs?) by ſuch by aſſes of ſecular Salaries, and humane depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances (when they have no <hi>tenure,</hi> but the good pleaſure of benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors) be warped, either to <hi>politer flatteries,</hi> or ſhamefull ſervities: ſo that people will in a ſhort time not know how to believe or eſteem ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one or the other.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What man, though never ſo vain and light, doth not abhor the mercenary lips and tongues of Miniſters? when in ſtead of uſing that Larcheſie, or liberty of ſpeech, which becomes Gods Ambaſſadours, they are like <hi>Micahs Levite,</hi> or <hi>Iereboams</hi> Prieſts, bowing downe to any <hi>Teraphins</hi> or <hi>Calves;</hi> and like <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets, ſaying no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what may <hi>pleaſe,</hi> though never ſo pernicious in the event, to Magiſtrates, Princes and People. Nothing will be more fulſome and contemptible than <hi>ſuch Preachers,</hi> who ſerve the Lord, that they may <hi>ſerve their bellies;</hi> and to ſerve both, they muſt ſerve <hi>the times,</hi> and in them the various luſts, humours and intereſts of men, be they never ſo extravagant; which way ſoever they liſt to modell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:124892:19"/> to civill power and policies.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Not but that Miniſters of the Goſpell as well (as other ſubjects) ought alwaies to bear all due reſpect to lawfull Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> and thoſe powers which are of God; yea and to bleſs God for any favour, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, or ingenuous maintenance they enjoy under them, ſhort of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</p>
            <p>I onely demonſtrate how great an abatement and fall it muſt be in point of former honor, ſubſiſtence and authority, for Miniſters to be deprived of thoſe <hi>Livings;</hi> in the midſt of which they quietly reſided, and wherein they were inſeated as fully and firmly during life, (and keeping within the compaſs of known Laws) as any other man in his <hi>Freehold:</hi> for theſe I ſay to be reduced from this legal <hi>tenure</hi> and <hi>propriety,</hi> to a meer arbitrary uncertainty; by way of ſtipend, and onely during pleaſure! where after much pains, and various compliances (which oft ſhrewdly wring &amp; ſtretch their conſciences) they may perhaps with much ſoliciting and attendance, obtaine ſome ſmall penſion; which if denied, they have no law to recover: and to get it they muſt, beſides weary journeys, crouch very low, and own as many maſters, (beſides their ſupreames) as there are Treaſurers, Clarks, and Officers, who have any capacity to deny, delay, or affront the poor men, until they ſacrifice as ſuppliants, ſome propitiation to them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Certainly the more liberall, honeſt, and ingenuous the ſpirits, ſpeech, and manners of Miniſters are, the greater is the <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>advancement</hi> of Religion. A ſervile Miniſter is prone to be the <hi>Divels Hackny,</hi> who will ride him with a bit and a ſpurre. Men are as other Creatures taught much to ſpeak as they are fed. Thoſe will eaſily have Bridles in Mens Jawes, who put bread into their mouths.</p>
            <p n="7">7. As the mindes of <hi>common people</hi> are, ſo are their manners: and as their Miniſters are, ſo for the moſt <hi>are peoples mindes.</hi> A baſe and indigent Miniſtry, (which <hi>follows the people as the taile, not leads them as the head</hi>) can produce nothing but meanneſs, ſervility, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs, indifferency, profaneſs, atheiſme, and irreligion in the generality of the people, as is evident both at home and abroad: where every bit the poor Miniſter eates, hath an hook or ſnare in it, which he muſt ſwallow: or elſe he ſhall be forced to mingle his bread with aſhes, and his drink with teares.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Beſides, theſe methods of mercenarineſs and ſervility will (as they have already) render Miniſters and Scholars every where Shrubs and muſhroomes, as to all greatneſs of learning, to all eminency of part, to all ingenuous freedom, to all vertuous conſtancy, and to all venerable authority; when they ſhould be as well grown, well watered, and well fenced Trees in the Garden of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yet is not this dependance upon the publike <hi>box</hi> and <hi>ſalary,</hi> where more ſence of honor, juſtice, and ingenuity may oft be exſpected, ſo pernicious, as that will be, which the <hi>policies of other</hi> meaner ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits do project (for there is no Mould ſo deformed and ugly, into which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:124892:19"/> ſome men do not deſigne to caſt the <hi>Miniſters of England,</hi>) (whom the Lord deliver.) Theſe would have not onely no <hi>Glebes,</hi> or <hi>Tithes,</hi> but no ſetled <hi>Penſions,</hi> or any <hi>conſtant Maintenance</hi> at all for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; but long to ſee them go up and down with their <hi>bag</hi> and <hi>bottle,</hi> to their good Maſters, and Dames: not like mendicant Friars, who do it by choice, and ſo with ſome honor, but theſe of neceſſity, attended with ſcorne; where, beſides the brow, coyneſs, the inſolencies and ſwellings of the givers, (which the poor Miniſter muſt bear, from thoſe, upon whoſe almes he muſt depend:) his hungry and flexible ſoul will ſoone be warpt to the warmer beames of the liberall hands that drop fatneſs, and wholly be withdrawn from any care or regard of the poorer ſort of people, who will be either wholly neglected, or with great indifferency ſlighted.</p>
            <p>Whereas the maintenance of Miniſters, as now ſetled in <hi>England,</hi> when it is worthy of able Miniſters, gives the <hi>poor</hi> as great an intereſt in the labours and love of their Miniſters, as the rich: yea and ſome portion alſo they enjoy of his maintenance, where himſelf is not <hi>one of the poor.</hi> The joint and common intereſt, which Miniſters have in the bleſſings of the earth with their people, cauſeth ſomething alſo of a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſympathy, and ſence: as to the ſeaſons, as good or bad; and as to the the hand of providence, toward the fruits of the earth.</p>
            <p>But it is eaſie to ſpell what is the meaning of this laſt project at leaſt: which is, not to have any able or <hi>worthy Miniſters</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> to preach, profeſs or maintaine the reformed religion. The burning and ſhining lights muſt either be <hi>quenched</hi> or <hi>ſtarved;</hi> that ſo the enemies of true Religion, may in the dark freely enjoy their <hi>obſcene mixtures</hi> of error, ignorance, profaneſs, and ſuperſtition: which ſome as earneſtly long for, as <hi>Theeves</hi> and <hi>Whores</hi> do for twilight: whoſe iſſue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other monſters, will be ſuch a race of Miniſters, as ſhall be the <hi>Creatures</hi> of the people, and their <hi>contempt</hi> too; <hi>dependants</hi> on them, and <hi>deſpiſed</hi> by them; as the Giants of old ſprung from the earth, and juſtly oppreſſed with it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But it is further urged; Many Godly people greivouſly complain of the <hi>ſcandal</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion</hi> of Tithes, both as to their conſciences, and their eſtates: Theſe in piety and prudence ought to be eaſed and relieved.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. As nothing is more tenderly to be conſidered, than the Conſciences of Chriſtians; So nothing is leſs to be made ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>cover</hi> to Mens ignorance, or a <hi>colour</hi> to their covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Pleadings of Conſcience ſerves no Mans turne for not paying <hi>Taxes</hi> to Souldiers; why ſhould it be good for not paying Tithes to Miniſters? ſince both are civill and ſecular things as to the matter, and the equity of both is juſtified in Scripture as well as reaſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not conſcience, but obſtinacy and contentiouſneſs, to deny or affirm without reaſon, neither proving what they aſſert, nor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering what is urged, from common equity, Scriptures analogy, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:124892:20"/> cuſtome, private donations, publike ſanctions, and Gods accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: as is in the caſe of Tithes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It were indeed a zeal according to knowledge to deny paying Tithes, to a <hi>Jewiſh Prieſt</hi> ſacrificing: but not ſo to pay them to a <hi>Jewiſh Miniſter</hi> preaching the Goſpel. The firſt is to be abhorred, ſince Chriſt is come and hath <hi>finiſhed</hi> all. The ſecond is to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that Chriſt come, and crucified, may be preached and believed on. The ſame action may be lawfull or unlawfull, according to the different ends, to which it is deſigned as a means. He that gives a poor man mony to buy him Tooles to work honeſtly, is charitable: but he that gives ſo much to a Thief to furniſh him with inſtruments of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and robbery, is blameable</p>
            <p n="5">5. As for theſe complainers in conſcience againſt Tithes, full as good and Godly men. Miniſters and others, complain of theſe complainers, as weak, ignorant, paſſionate, and imprudent: or elſe very peeviſh unjuſt, covetous, and violent perturbers of the publike Ordinance. Beſides, for the moſt part they are cauſleſly clamorous and <hi>unreaſonably impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune:</hi> ſince few of theſe, either pay any Tithes at all, or any thing elſe to any Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and if they do, it is full ſore <hi>againſt</hi> their wills. Their greateſt grief and burthen is, that they may not keep their Tithes to themſelves, to which they can pretend no more right, then a Tenant can to detaine his Rent from his Landlord: Nor were they ever heard to complain of the load and burthen of <hi>Tithes</hi> taken to themſelves, were they never ſo heavy, both in the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and in the injuſtice.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But if it may indeed be a <hi>burthen</hi> to ſome mens eſtates, that are weak; or to their mindes, that are illiberall and loth to pay Tithes to their Miniſters; will not the ſame Plea ly againſt all Rents and civill charges laid on lands and eſtates of poor men! But no Godly man (though poor) will in conſcience, becauſe he cannot in juſtice, deſire or expect, that he ſhould be eaſed of any charge or civill burthen, by inflicting injuries on other men; leaſt of all on Miniſters, who, as Gods labourers, merit their wages.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But people grudge that Miniſters ſhould have the benefit of all that coſt and labour, by which they <hi>mend</hi> and <hi>improve</hi> their Lands: They could afford them a tenth of the Rent, but not of their ſtock and labours. Poor men, how well they deſerve, and how well pleaſed they would be with a <hi>barren untilled, unimproved</hi> Miniſtry! Let any Miniſters ſtock be never ſo great of learning and knowledge; let him dayly with great coſt in books and paines in his ſtudies, improve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for Gods glory, and peoples good: Is there not as much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and juſtice, he ſhould have the benefit of their lands improved, as they ſhould have of his gifts and talents increaſed? whereto he is dayly intent, by ſtudy and prayer, that his profiting may appear to all men.</p>
            <p n="8">8. For that gliſtering of godlineſs, which ſome men make a ſhew of, againſt Miniſters Tythes; 1. It is no ſigne of ſolid and true godlineſs,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:124892:20"/> to <hi>with-hold good from them to whom it is due, Pro.</hi> 3.27. To deprive the labourer of his hire; to deny men that honeſt ſubſiſtence which is theirs by the appointment of the Law, and by the merit of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The firſt thing required in golineſs, is to do Juſtice, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.8. Equity and Piety never claſh or interfere; nor is there any fear of ſin or ſuperſtition in giving to every one, what is theirs by law of civil ſociety. A Chriſtian ought to pay his rent to a Turk, Jew, or Heathen-Landlord, though he knew they imployed it to Idolatrous &amp; ſuperſtitious uſes. And ſhall it be urged as godlineſs, by Chriſtians, to deny the paying of tythes, which is but as out of their rent, to a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt; which by free gift he lawfully might; and by law he neceſſarily ought to do!</p>
            <p n="3">3. How can ſuch godlineſs, and unjuſtice be reconciled? or how can ſuch <hi>covetous ſcruplers</hi> hope to enter into heaven, whoſe righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſo far from exceeding, that it comes far ſhort of that of the Scribes and Phariſees? They paid <hi>Tythes</hi> of all they had, which Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. commended, and joynes with Moral and great duties; theſe of <hi>nothing</hi> they have. How far from fulfilling the Apoſtolical and divine commands, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. Let them that <hi>is taught, communicate to him that teacheth in all good things:</hi> Theſe communicate of no good thing, or onely in a <hi>diſorderly</hi> way, to whom they liſt, and what they liſt; neither regarding Gods example and proportion in old, nor his direction and ordinance in the new Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Godly men ought to conſider, that the temptation is eaſie and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious in matters of <hi>profit,</hi> to pretend conſcience; it is a Chymiſtry ſome men have, to turne <hi>godlineſs into gain,</hi> which will undo them at laſt. Covetous ſcruples uſually reſolve into mens owne profit, as Ice into water; but never into expences, or other mens benefits.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It were a ſure ſign of godlineſs, for men to be rather ſelf-denying in point of profit, then defrauding others; to pay rather more then leſs; to be willing to encourage good Miniſters, not to reproach and impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them; this would expreſs a godlineſs, not in the form of talkative inconſtancy, and thrifty pragmaticalneſs, but of judicious ſincerity, and generous charity.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Truly, Godly men might ſoon eaſe themſelves of this ſcruple in point of conſcience, that in ſtead in paying a tenth, they paid a ninth, or ſixth; which at once may ſatisfie Gods ordinance, the law of the land, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters claim, and their owne conſciences; beſides their liberality will ſupererogate, and to their honour exceed what Miniſters could ask, or any man expect of them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is ſtrange that the complaint and clamour againſt Tythes ſhould never be heard till of late, and now ſo few perſons of either eſtates or eminent worth are found in it; Is it becauſe men of mean eſtates and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious mindes, take confidence to deſire any thing which reaſon and juſtice deny yet deſpair of nothing that numbers and power can reach?
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:124892:21"/> or are theſe in the ſimplicity of their ſouls ſet on by others more crafty, whoſe drift is againſt the Miniſtry, more then the maintenance? their aim is not that there be no Tythes for Miniſters to receive, but no reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters to receive Tythes.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The ſcruple of conſcience would lye more direct againſt theſe mens receiving <hi>Tythes</hi> themſelves, as they oft do without any check in impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations, then in paying them to Miniſters; Since the firſt is but an aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or <hi>by-blow,</hi> alien and hid from the chief intent and end of the Donors, which was for the maintenance of Chriſts Miniſters and ſervice; and however by Law they are made as a lay fee in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. dayes; yet this was firſt grounded on the <hi>Popes Authority</hi> (it may be with no ill intent) who took them from the rectories or cures, and applyed them to Covents or Monaſteries; yet in the Court of Conſcience the Popes act was injurious at firſt, in alienating the means from the Miniſter, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent, from whence in the event have followed ſo many poor livings, poor Miniſters, and poor ſouls. How can an injury be made good by ſucceſſion, or juſt by ſhifting from hand to hand? It is ſtrange theſe godly men do not ſcruple to make good any Act of the Popes, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy any favour and indulgence on his account in their impropriate tythes and Parſonages which they enjoy.</p>
            <p n="9">9. But they would not have Miniſters Tythe-coveters. O godly jealouſie! Nor would Miniſters have any of theſe cautious objecters coveters of Tythes; which they then do ſinfully and ſordidly, when they have no right to them, as they have not by Gods or mans law: there is no ſin is coveting what is a mans owne, by all right both divine and humane. But may they not be as much coveters of Penſions, as of Tythes? or of benevolences as of either? and moſt of all prone to be cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of other men eſtates, when they have no certainty of their owne?</p>
            <p n="10">10. Laſtly, I anſwer to theſe complainers, If perſons in publick place ſhall alwaies be altering and changing, until men ceaſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, or to project amendments, they ſhall never want either <hi>work or woe,</hi> and never enjoy the fruit of their counſels or labours. For ſuch is the proud envious nature of man, that what one plants, another ſeeks to pull up; what one builds another pulls downe; what one approves, another abhors. Veſſels with large ſayles have not alwaies anſwerable blaſt. Some mens conſciences carrie little or no ſcience with them; their cryes <hi>portend no wooll,</hi> nor do their complaints intend any reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: wiſe men ought impartially to caſt <hi>anchor,</hi> and fix in juſt reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions once taken, either by their fore-fathers or themſelves, ſo to bring the publick to <hi>the haven</hi> of <hi>conſiſtence:</hi> not to be toſſed to and fro with every winde of fancy or faction: nor may they ſuffer the waters to be troubled, ſo oft as ſome men hope to catch fiſh; though it be to the Shipwrack undoing and drowning of many men far their betters eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But the Country people, or Farmours and Yeomen, are againſt Tythes: theſe would have them taken away.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:124892:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It was neither piety nor prudence in <hi>Pilate</hi> to condemn Chriſt to be crucified, that he might pleaſe the peoples <hi>clamour.</hi> Wiſe men muſt not regard what, but upon what ground common people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that which threatens any man with injury.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, it is certain, This is not <hi>the deſire</hi> of either the wiſeſt, beſt, or moſt <hi>Country-men;</hi> the noiſe is not the voice of many and <hi>great waters,</hi> but of ſhallow and ſudden torrents.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Such as do urge the taking away of Tythes, do it moſt what upon a falſe <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> and are tempted by a ſtrange, yet vaine <hi>deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (which is like the <hi>Jack-daw</hi> in the Fable, who hoped he ſhould get the morſel which the Eagle let fal, when indeed the Fox ran away with it.) Poor men, they flatter themſelves, that if Tythes be once taken from Miniſters hands, they will preſently fall into their laps, &amp; reſt in their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. It is pity, and yet it is but juſt the country-ſimplicity ſhould be thus gulled. Wiſe Farmers are got beyond theſe Fairy-fancies; and the event will confute the others golden dreams, when they ſhall ſee Tythes if taken from Miniſters, either turn to the increaſe of their Landlords rents, as purchaſed by them; or elſe required by others, more ſevere exactors then ever Miniſters were: After this, they ſhall have either no Miniſters, or at a new charge, when Tythes are gone another way, as little to their eaſe, as nothing to their benefit.</p>
            <p>None but weak men can ſuppoſe, that men in power will ever be ſo prodigal, as to remit of courteſie either to Landlords or Tenant ſo conſiderable a Revenue: to which neither of them have any right or ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in Law or Equity.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Others pretend, as a point of prudentiall thrift, that <hi>Tithes</hi> are too much for Miniſters, leſs will ſerve their turnes; part of what they have more then enough, may help to defray publike charges, or eaſe the people, who by Tithes and other exactions are much impoveriſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no reaſon to put the after-burthens of people upon the ſcore of Tithes, which was long before theſe civill taxes, and to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end: nor do they riſe out of any private mans Eſtate, but out of a publike patrimony, to which God is proprietor, and his Miniſters are his penſioners.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a project unworthy the honor of this Nation, which is bleſſed with a rich and good Land, to eaſe themſelves by injuring God and his Miniſters, or to repine at that coſt beſtowed on Chirſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. No wiſe or Godly man ever thought, or by experience found his paying Tithes to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, was either moth, or worm to his eſtate, or to the publike; but rather a protection and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the remaining parts. The due payment of them is rather, as the Jews obſerve, a <hi>fatning</hi> and <hi>improving</hi> of mens eſtates and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: uſually they get moſt good by the Miniſters pains, who make moſt conſcience to pay them their dues; which is ſeldome done cheerfully and exactly, unleſs, where the oyl of love ſoftens the vigor of the Law.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:124892:22"/>4. For the <hi>too much,</hi> which is objected with as little truth, as much envy, all experience confutes it, which ſhews that Miniſters in every Country, living with the ſevereſt thrift becoming men of any charity and hoſpitality, yet dye poor or mean at beſt, leaving Widowes and Poſterity to conflict with many difficulties, and to finde few friends. It is not comely in piety, charity, or prudence, to object ſuperfluity, where there is ſeldom competency, and for the moſt part neceſſity. Many livings affording but little livelihood to the Miniſter, by that time they are pared with thoſe expences which are charged on them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But many Miniſters are unworthy of their maintenance, ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in abilities, others negligent in their duties, many ſcandalous in their manners. Theſe in prudence ought to be looked to, that at leaſt Drones may not devour the Hony intended for induſtrious Bees.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This indeed were worthy of wiſe and good Mens ſerious conſideration and reformation. But there is one thing never moved by the Vulgar, which I humbly propound. Many able, induſtrious, and moſt unblameable Miniſters are deprived of all means, and diſabled both to do that work, for which God hath enbled them, and to enjoy that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit which their merit and the Laws have made but their due. Whoſe <hi>Sequeſtrations,</hi> which ſeemed but temporary, during the agony and conteſt of parties, is become perpetuall and total deprivation. Theſe worthy and diſtreſſed Miniſters, in juſtice and charity, ought to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered firſt, ſince the prime work of juſtice is rather to preſerve a good Man, then to puniſh one that is bad.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How farre the complaint againſt ſome Miniſters is true, I know not, but I believe, as to farre the major part is very falſe. What is amiſs wiſe and good Governours may amend, by wholeſome admonition, or ſeverer cenſures.</p>
            <p>But to aſperſe all, becauſe ſome may be faulty, or to deſtroy all for ſome mens demerits, is upon no better principle of Prudence, than it would be to ſtarve men in health, becauſe ſick men can't bear their food; or to deny labourers their hire, becauſe of ſome loiterers in the field; or to cut off ſound parts, becauſe ſome are infected or gangren'd.</p>
            <p n="8">8. But many things (they ſay) might no doubt be better ordered in the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Tythes, ſo to avoid the unkinde ſuits, vexations and differences which oft ariſe between Miniſters and people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truely I think ſo too: all good Miniſters would be glad to enjoy the real fruits of ſuch ſober and righteous wiſdom. Let but the foundation ſtand as ſetled on lands, (for other can no man lay, either pleaſing or permanent) in Gods name remedy the inconveniences; which are not many; nor riſing out of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing, ſo much as out of mans paſſions and infirmities. Nor are they hard to be remedied; although I take it to be preſumption for any private man publikely to propound any particular way and method, till he is called; and hath firſt privately propounded it. It is eaſie to make the matter of Tythes as quiet and eaſie a revenue, as any rent in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mean while, grave and wiſe Miniſters do eaſily avoid unhandſom contentions; wherein they are rather ſufferers then actors; if they meet with people of any juſtice or conſcience, whoſe Piety hath not eaten out all Humanity; or whoſe Religion is not to cozen their Miniſters, but rather to give them their due, both in the merit of their labours in Gods Ordinance and the Laws appointment.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:124892:22"/>
            <p>In the laſt place, the policy and thrift of ſome men, urge in point of prudence; That however Miniſters bred in <hi>Schools and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> are leſſe able or willing to maintain themſelves by other honeſt imployments, and alſo muſt wholly depend on their Church-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings; (having ſeldom any great ſtock or eſtate of their own beſides) yet there are now ſtore of gifted men riſen up, who are able and willing to maintain themſelves and their families at their own charges, and to preach the Goſpel <hi>gratis</hi> to the people; ſo that Tithes might be well ſpared as to Miniſters, and imployed ſome other way to eaſe the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. I do not deſpiſe nor diſparage the gifts of any men, whoſe abilities in a way of Order and Authority, becoming the honour of Religion, and the humility of grave and ſober Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, may be really uſeful to Gods glory, and peoples good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But it is to be conſidered, that many of theſe Voluntiers, who obtrude themſelves to the work of the Miniſtry, out of an opinion of their gifts; neither know the weight of the work, nor their own weakneſs and unproportionableneſs; <hi>elſe,</hi> they would not take the Lamp in one hand, and the Pitcher in the other; or unequally yoke the Miniſter and Mechanick together; which is not to be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> practice, unleſs men had that Apoſtles gifts who bids <hi>Timothy</hi> give himſelf ſolely and wholly to the <hi>work of the Miniſtry,</hi> without the intanglement of any other Calling, as his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15. If private <hi>preſumptions,</hi> enable men, and inveſt them into places of Office; what Souldier will not be a <hi>Colonel</hi> or <hi>General</hi> preſently? what Barreſter will not be a Judge? what mean man will not fancy himſelf fit to be Magiſtrate, as well as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter?</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Commonneſs</hi> or <hi>Cheapneſs</hi> of men that will needs be Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, adds no value or worth to them, in compariſon of able Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that need not to be aſhamed; no more then Braſs Farthings turn to be Angels of gold, becauſe they are currant among poor people.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Forwardneſs to the work of the Miniſtry, is no Argument of ſufficiency to that work; which well conſidered, would ſcare an Angel from it; till God ſent him to be a Miniſtring ſpirit for the good of the Church.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But theſe cheap <hi>ſelf-ſending</hi> men eaſily relieve themſelves, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as little conſcience (when they find the work too heavy for them) to lay it down, and take off their hand from the Plough, as they did to take the one up, or to put their hand uncalled to the other.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Some of theſe pretenders to <hi>extraordinary</hi> gifts, are found to be but Juglers, under diſguiſes; concealing the <hi>learned Education</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:124892:23"/> they have had at home or abroad, that they may gain the more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and admiration from the vulgar, in order to advance the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign they drive; which is to diſgrace and overthrow the Miniſters and Miniſtry of this Reformed Church.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is evident, theſe free and forward Teachers will endure to take, and expect to have a good penſion for their pains, when once they find ſuch a gale of applauſe, as incourageth them wholly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture their fortunes in this Veſſel. Nor doth it at all trouble them to take the Tithes or benefits of other mens Livings, if once they can get ſuch a Title to them, as they may diſcretly leave their Trades.</p>
            <p n="8">8. What the Miniſterial ſufficiencies of theſe ſo <hi>free</hi> and <hi>frugal</hi> Maſters are, compared to thoſe which able Miniſters have had, and ſtill have, in knowledge and utterance of Divine Myſteries, it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter other men ſhould judge and declare, then any of our ſelves, to you; we dare appeal to your own experiences, who know both: yea, let the righteous Lord judge between them and us.</p>
            <p n="9">9. It is pity the cheapneſs and eaſineſs of thoſe mens preaching, (if it be ſuch) ſhould be the only motive to commend them as a better bargain to peoples ſouls: Tithes are ill ſaved, with the hazard of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Salvation:</hi> If the folly and madneſs of people will needs have them (though they hereafter ſcorn and abhor them) yet there is no reaſon they ſhould thruſt Miniſters out of their places, or deprive them of their rights due to them, and by no Law forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; only to make way for theſe <hi>forward Orators;</hi> whom neither preaching, nor praying, ſpeaking, or writing, have yet ſo advanced in wiſe and ſober Chriſtians eſteem, as to make them either eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, deſired, or unpitied.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Laſtly, Wiſe men muſt conſider, not what the Vulgar eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deſires or diſlikes in a fit of worldly-wantonneſs, thrift, faction, or diſcontent; (in which diſtempers they will caſt off with murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reproach, both <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> their ableſt Governours, and faithfulleſt Miniſters) but Rulers ought to regard what is beſt for peoples Temporal and Eternal welfare (though in the preſent fit it diſpleaſe them;) alſo what is really for the honour of Religion the glory of God, and the welfare of a Nation. The diſordered Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of people, if humored, (as feaveriſh perſons) will ſoon make them as miſerable, as they are unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note>Thus have I endeavoured as briefly as I could (with your leave and patience, Gentlemen) to preſent to your view theſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons touching Miniſters maintenance by Tithes here in <hi>England:</hi> From which I have ſought, in the firſt place, with all cleareneſs of reaſon, calmneſs of aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion, and uprightneſs of conſcience to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:124892:23"/> all aſperſions and ſuſpition of any thing ſinful or unlawful in them, having demonſtrated the Equity and Piety of them, both in general as a reward, and in particular, as ſo proportioned, according to Gods command or patern of old, and his reference or appointment to thoſe precedents in the New Teſtament, to which the devotion of primitive Chriſtians, the cuſtome of all ſetled Churches, the will of the donors, and the eſtabliſhment of the Civil Laws of this Nation are conform.</p>
            <p>In the 2. place, I have ſalved the chief inconveniences, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſatisfie the pretences of prudence in point of innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or altering the way of this maintenance by Tithes.</p>
            <p>Not but that here I well remember, how I have <hi>oher where wrote,</hi> and publiſhed in another method, my judgment touching this ſubject. Where being to deal, as in other grand diſputes, with men wiſe in their own conceits, I was forced with weight of reaſon, and ſome earneſtnes of expreſſion many times to bray them in a Mortar; not out of my own <hi>genius</hi> or propenſity to ſtrive or conteſt; but urged by the obſtinacy of that folly which hath by words and deeds been lately diſcovered with moſt uncomly <hi>boſtings,</hi> and unjuſt <hi>reproaches</hi> againſt the office, honor, authority, maintenance, and very being of the Miniſters of <hi>England;</hi> In whoſe behalf I held it my duty, not to be ſilent; and ſo to ſpeak as might ſhew how much I reverenced their worth, and how little I feared the petulancy of their enemyes, who beyond any example in any Chriſtian Nation, have endeavoured under pretences of ſpecial Sanctity and Reformation, to diſgrace and deſtroy the ableſt Preachers and moſt excellent Profeſſors of true Religion in the Nation.</p>
            <p>But to you, Gentlemen, as <hi>Perſons</hi> now in <hi>power</hi> and counſel, I do with all gravity, modſty, calmneſſe, and humility preſent theſe conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Not, but that I wel underſtand, by what I have ſeen and read, how impertinent and uſeleſs ſuch adreſſes by the Pen, for the moſt part are to men <hi>confident of their power,</hi> byaſed with prejudices, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with paſſions: if learned and Godly men ſhould write as many Books as the <hi>World would contain,</hi> they ſhould do but little good. The <hi>calmeſt Remonſtrances,</hi> which Reaſon, Religion, Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Chriſtianity, Equity or Piety, Charity, or Conſcience, Hiſtory, or Experience afford, oft prove as the Oration in <hi>Tacitus,</hi> of <hi>Muſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> (a grave and learned Senator) to the mutinous <hi>Soldiers:</hi> which at firſt was unwelcome, next tedious, after ridiculous, at laſt dangerous to that unſeaſonable Orator.</p>
            <p>This made me ſomtime think it the beſt and prudenteſt way for Miniſters to ſtand ſtill and wait for <hi>the Salvation of God, in an evil time</hi> to <hi>be ſilent,</hi> after the example of their Lord Chriſt to hold their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:124892:24"/> Peace, though they be as Sheep under the Shearers hands, and by ſome appointed to be ſlain; and the rather, leſt ſome mens <hi>cruelty</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice againſt Miniſters might poſſibly gain ſome reputation by the <hi>reaſons publikely</hi> offered to them in behalf of Miniſters rights, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blikely refuſed by them; which muſt of courſe be traduced as weak and unſufficient to preſerve their intereſts, which wilful and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men are <hi>reſolved to</hi> deſtroy.</p>
            <p>But I have learned never to fear or deſpair in a good and juſt cauſe, ſuch as I take this to be which I humbly preſent <hi>before</hi> you; Among whom I doubt not but the diſtreſſed Miniſters of this Church ſhall find ſome friends.</p>
            <p>However, you have invited us not to betray our cauſe by our ſilence; leſt preſent and after ages ſhould ſuſpect us unable or aſhamed to juſtify what we do or deſire. By the <hi>pregnancy of reaſons,</hi> which I have here recorded, and with all due reſpect tendered to you, this age and poſterity may judg the <hi>obſtinacie</hi> of that folly, which will determine of things, it underſtands not; and the violence of that fury, which will cut in ſunder that knot by force, which with juſtice and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciene it cannot untie.</p>
            <p>But I muſt preſume (till I find the contrary) that you as Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Chriſtians will bear the words of Truth and ſoberneſs; That your Counſels and deſignes are not ſwayed, by vulgar <hi>Clamors,</hi> and factious diſcontents, but by Rational, Equitable, and Religious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations; Looking not only how to attemper your reſolutions to preſent diſtempers, and to humor the <hi>Paroxiſmes</hi> of diſeaſes; but alſo how to recover the health and happineſs of this ſorely toſſed and afflicted Church and Nation. To which the overthrowing of maintenance and Miniſtry will contribute very little.</p>
            <p>This confidence hath made me once more, in a matter of ſo grand concernment, to adventure upon this part of pious importunity; which God knows (in the midſt of many confeſſed infirmities) ayms at nothing but thoſe great and good ends of which I ſhall at laſt day be leaſt aſhamed before God, Angels and men. At whoſe great &amp; impartiall tribunal, ſince you alſo muſt appear, it higly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes, you and all of us, to avoid the contracting any further <hi>guilt of Sacriledg</hi> upon your ſouls and the Nation. Which of all crying ſins is leaſt taken notice of by men in power; ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome pardoned, becauſe ſeldome repented of; and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome repented of, becauſe true repentance requires juſt Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>If the fear of <hi>God be before your eyes,</hi> you will not be as a people <hi>that ſtrives with the Prieſt.</hi> Nor will you treat ſo many learned, grave and holy men, with a <hi>Soldierly roughnes, Nabalitick churliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and fanatick fury. But remember your, and their God; your,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:124892:24"/> and their Judg, your and their Saviour; To whoſe labours, love, and faithfulneſs you and your Fore-fathers owe the reformation and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of true Religion hitherto. However they are now looked upon us as afflicted of God, and forſaken of men, yet their judgment and reward are with the Moſt High</p>
            <p>Nor hath any oppreſſion or fear ſo far diſordered them, but that their <hi>wiſdome remains</hi> with them; as perſons very ſenſible of right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, juſtice, honor, and religion; both in its doctrine, and its fruits; in its profeſſion, and its power, which makes men by grace and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs like to God, not in words onely, but in deeds.</p>
            <p>To which that you be not ſtrangers, how can you further caſt us off to Vulgar condition &amp; ſcorn; expoſing us to fight with <hi>beaſts,</hi> &amp; to be trampled under the feet of <hi>unreaſonable men,</hi> who threaten as you may eaſily know) the utter ruine and extirpation of the Miniſtry of this Church, and the Reformed Religion; which I beſeech God of his mercy to prevent, and if it be his will, by <hi>your</hi> means.</p>
            <p>No work is indeed more worthy of thoſe that would approve themſelves, holy, zealous and good men, then a ſerious and effectual regard toward the diſtreſſed <hi>miniſtry of Chriſt</hi> in this Church, to hear their complaints, to lay to heart their burthens, their diſcouragments, the incompetency and wretchedneſs of their maintenance in many places. Hence the decay of their parts, ſtudies, reputation and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority among people. This drawes after it the neglect &amp; contempt of all Holy miniſtrations and duties; This portends the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uine of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſouls in <hi>England</hi> &amp; in <hi>Wales</hi> too; as it is this day, by the ſad deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; darkneſs, which is come upon many places; eſpecially in <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Glory <hi>of your</hi> God, the Honor <hi>of your</hi> Saviour, the <hi>Souls of your</hi> poor Brethren call for from wiſe and Godly men ſpeedy, and real endeavours to ſetle by ſome means that ſo oft in vain promiſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petencie of maintenance; which will require and bear that compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of Miniſters abilities in every place, which is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>That ſo the order, honour, and beauty of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is grievouſly ſhaken, battered, and threatens to fall, may be reſtored and eſtabliſhed; That the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, may with power and authority be propagated; which is never to be done by <hi>arbitrary,</hi> weak, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly <hi>teachers;</hi> by ambulatory <hi>penſioners,</hi> by vagrant and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant journeymen, whoſe feeble and unfrequent ſtrokes, will never be able with a touch and away, to forge peoples hard hearts either to faith, or Repentance; to true knowledg or devotion: That there is in all reaſon required, to ſo good &amp; great a work, able, grave, and godly Miniſters, every where comfortably <hi>reſiding,</hi> who by the inſtancy of ſound <hi>Preaching,</hi> by ferventy of judicious <hi>praying,</hi> and by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of <hi>holy living,</hi> may guide people in the way of true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:124892:25"/>
            <p>But I have done, committing your hearts to God, who is the beſt guide and ſevereſt ſearcher of them.</p>
            <p>I onely leave this laſt ſigh or grone of the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> with you;</p>
            <q>
               <p>If all pleas of piety and juſtice, of merit and gratitude, of Laws divine and humane, of honour, learning, and civility, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in behalf of the able, and faithful Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> both in reſpect of their maintenaunce, and Miniſtry, their aliment, and imployment, ſhall on all ſides find a deaf ear, which is reſolved to deſert and deſtroy them, rather than with patience to hear them, or with juſtice to preſerve them and their rights; If neither the wiſe, nor the ſtrong, nor the great, nor the good delight further in us; If for ſome mens follies in this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we muſt be made as the <hi>tail</hi> and not the <hi>head,</hi> fitted to be cut off <hi>root and branch,</hi> in one day; if our ruines muſt adorn the triumphs of our enemies, if the cries and tears of our diſtreſſed families muſt be made the Muſick and Wine of thoſe who have a long time hated us, and our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion; if there be no remedy to be found either in mens juſtice or compaſſion, but we muſt at laſt come to the fiery tryall.</p>
               <p>Yet we ſhall (as we have cauſe) lay our hands on our mouths, and either be ſilent with humble aſtoniſhment; or ſay no more but, <hi>It is the Lord, let him do as ſeemeth good in his ſight.</hi> What ever hard meaſure, or injuſtice, may be in the Inſtruments, there can be nothing but <hi>Juſtice</hi> in his permiſſions, and there may be <hi>mercy</hi> in his puniſhments; which will then appear, when his fatherly ſtrokes are ſo ſanctified to us, as to make us turn to him that hath ſmitten us, and hath been ſmitten by us.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
